Advertise your product or brand here contact www.OpenSubtitles.org today
Anuncie su producto o marca aquם contבctenos www.OpenSubtitles.org hoy
All right, sweet pea, it's time for you to go to bed.
Preciosa, es hora de dormir.
Mommy, would you ask Daddy to come tuck me in?
Puedes decirle a papi que venga a arroparme, mami?
No, he's at work tonight at the fire station.
Estב trabajando en la estaciףn de bomberos.
But he'll be home tomorrow night.
Pero volverב maסana en la noche.
Mommy, I want to marry Daddy.
Mami, quiero casarme con papi.
You do? Catherine, you can't marry Daddy.
De verdad? Catherine, no puedes casarte con papi.
He's my husband.
ֹl es mi esposo.
Well, when you're done being married, can I have him?
Cuבndo te canses de estar casada con יl me lo das?
We'll never be done. You'll have to marry somebody else.
Nunca nos vamos a separar. Tendrבs que casarte con otro.
Can I wear a white dress and white gloves?
Me puedo poner un vestido blanco y guantes?
Sure, if you want to.
Claro, si tת quieres.
Will we live happily after ever?
Y viviremos felices para siempre?
If you marry somebody who really, really loves you.
Si te casas con alguien que te quiera de verdad.
Like Daddy?
Cףmo papi?
Yes, like Daddy.
Sם, como papi.
- Terrell, man, my bad out there. - This ain't no game.
- Terrel, amigo, fue mi culpa. - Esto no es juego.
You playing with people lives.
Juegas con vidas.
Come on, man.
Vamos, hombre.
Eric, he's got a right to be upset.
Eric, tiene razףn de estar enojado.
You left him in a dangerous spot and tried to be a hero.
Lo dejaste en un lugar peligroso para hacerte el hיroe.
I thought I heard someone calling for help.
Creם escuchar a alguien que pedםa ayuda.
It was coming from outside the building.
Venםa de afuera del edificio.
It was dark, I couldn't see.
Estaba oscuro, no pude ver.
That's why you stay with your partner. He had to assume...
Por eso debes quedarte con tu compaסero, יl asumiף...
...that something happened to you and you needed his help.
...que algo te habםa pasado y que necesitabas su ayuda.
You never leave your partner, especially in a fire.
Nunca abandones a tu compaסero especialmente en un incendio.
You give him some time and then give him an apology.
Dale tiempo y luego discתlpate.
- And make it sincere. - Yes, sir.
- Y que suene sincero. - Sם, seסor.
- Hey, Tasha. - Oh, hey, Cat.
- Hola, Tasha. - Oh, hola, Cat.
Just saw you on TV. Looking good.
Acabo de verte en la tele. Saliste bien.
Oh, I missed it. I was giving a tour of the new cancer wing.
Me lo perdם. Estaba dando un tour en la nueva בrea de oncologםa.
- Hey, has Robin left yet? - No, she's here.
- Robin ya se fue? - No, estב aquם.
Robin, Cat's here.
Robin, Cat estב aquם.
- Hey. - How are you?
- Hola. - Cףmo estבs?
I'm good. How are you?
Bien. Y tת?
Good. Hey, are we still on for tomorrow?
Bien. Sigue en pie lo de maסana?
Yeah, 4:00. You still want those scented candles, right?
Sם, 4:00. Todavםa quieres las velas aromבticas, no?
Oh, absolutely. Bring them on.
Claro, trבelas.
- I wanna try them all. - Good.
- Quiero probarlas todas. - Que bien.
I'm going to see my parents this weekend.
Voy a visitar a mis padres este fin de semana.
- I thought they might like some too. - Oh, how are they?
- Podrםan querer unas tambiיn. - Cףmo estבn?
Do you know it's been a year since Mom's stroke?
Sabes que ya pasף un aסo desde el ataque de mamב?
I've been trying to get her a new bed and wheelchair...
He tratado de conseguirle una cama especial y una silla de ruedas...
...but their insurance doesn't cover it.
...pero el seguro no las cubre.
I don't know. It's so frustrating for my dad.
Es tan frustrante para papב.
He wants to help her too, but he can't afford it either.
El quiere ayudarla pero tampoco puede pagarlas.
- I am so sorry. - Yeah, it's all right.
- Lo siento. - Sם, estב bien.
Anyway, well, I need to run.
Bueno, me voy corriendo.
- But I'll see you tomorrow, right? - I'll see you.
- Pero nos veremos maסana, no? - Nos vemos.
- Okay, bye. - Bye.
- Muy bien, adiףs. - Adiףs.
- Hey, Catherine. - I'm so sorry, Dr. Keller.
- Hola, Catherine. - Perdone, Dr. Keller.
Call me Gavin, please.
Llבmeme Gavin, por favor.
Gavin, sorry for almost running you over.
Gavin, perdףname por casi atropellarte.
- Anytime. It's good to see you. - You too. Take care.
- Cuando quieras. Que bueno verte. - Igualmente, cuםdate.
Sweet girl.
Dulce muchacha.
- Tasha, will you file this for me? - Sure, doctor.
- Me archivarםas esto, Tasha? - Claro, doctor.
If I didn't know any better, I'd say the doctor has a thing for Cat.
Si no lo conociera tan bien, dirםa que al doctor le gusta Cat.
- Hi, sweetheart. - Hey, Daddy.
- Hola, preciosa. - Hola papi.
- How are you? - Oh, great. Good to see you.
- Cףmo estבs? - Muy bien, que bueno verte.
You too.
Igual.
Hey, Mama. How are you, huh?
Hola, mamב. Cףmo estבs?
She's doing great today.
Estב mejor hoy.
Can I get you something to drink, dear?
Quieres algo de tomar, querida?
- Do you have any sweet tea? - With lemon?
- Tienes tי dulce? - Con limףn?
You know me.
Me conoces.
Oh, Mama, I wish we could talk.
Oh, mamב, ojalב pudiיramos hablar.
It's been so long since I heard your voice.
Hace tanto que no oigo tu voz.
I miss you.
Te extraסo.
- You have breakfast already? - Yes.
- Ya desayunaste? - Sם.
- What'd you eat? - I had the last bagel and a yogurt.
- Quי comiste? - El תltimo pan y un yogurt.
Are you planning on making a grocery trip soon?
Piensas ir al supermercado pronto?
Caleb, you work 24 hours and then you're off for 48.
Caleb, trabajas 24 horas y tienes libres 48.
- You've got more time to go than I do. - I asked a simple question.
- Tienes mבs tiempo que yo. - Fue una simple pregunta.
You don't need to get smart with me. At least save me some breakfast.
No tienes que ser sarcבstica. Al menos dיjame algo de desayuno.
I never know when you're coming or going. You don't tell me.
Nunca sי cuando vas y vienes. Nunca me dices.
Catherine, what is your problem?
Cuבl es el problema, Catherine?
Did I offend you by walking in the door?
Te ofendם al pasar por la puerta?
You can't expect me to work every day and get the groceries...
No puedes esperar que trabaje todo el dםa, vaya al supermercado...
...while you look at trash on the Internet dreaming about your boat.
...mientras tu miras basura en internet y sueסas con tu barco.
You chose to take this job.
Tת escogiste este trabajo.
- No one said you had to work full-time. - We need the income.
- Nadie te lo pidiף. - Necesitamos el dinero.
Especially since you tuck away a third of your salary...
Especialmente desde que tomas un tercio de tu sueldo...
...saving for a boat we don't need.
...para comprar un barco que no necesitamos.
You've got $24,000 in savings when things in our house need fixing.
Tienes 24.000 dףlares ahorrados y hay cosas sin arreglar en casa.
Like what?
Cףmo quי?
The back door needs to be painted, the yard needs landscaping.
Pintar la puerta de atrבs, arreglar el jardםn.
And I wanna put more shelves in the closet.
Y mבs estantes en mi clףset.
Those are called preferences. Those are not needs.
Esas son preferencias. No necesidades.
There's a difference. If you wanna spend your money on that stuff, fine.
Es diferente. Si quieres gastar tu dinero en eso, muy bien.
I've been saving for my boat for years. You're not taking that from me.
Yo he ahorrado por aסos para mi barco, no me lo quitarבs.
This is so pointless. I don't have time for this.
No tiene caso. No tengo tiempo para esto.
Yeah, shut the door on your way out.
Sם, cierra la puerta cuando salgas.
It ain't working, Michael.
No funciona, Michael.
How is it that I get respect everywhere I go...
Cףmo puede ser que me respeten en todas partes...
...except in my own house?
...excepto en mi casa?
I've been there, and it's a hard place to be.
Me ha pasado y es muy duro.
What'd you do about it?
Y quי hiciste?
I realized that it wasn't my marriage that was broken.
Entendם que no era que mi matrimonio estuviera roto.
I just didn't know how to make it work.
Sino que simplemente yo no sabםa hacerlo funcionar.
What does that mean?
Quי significa eso?
That treadmill's not broken.
Que el molino no estב roto.
But if you don't know how to run it, it ain't gonna work for you.
Pero si no sabes usarlo, no te funcionarב.
You saying I need counseling?
Dices que necesitamos terapia?
Well, I think everybody needs counseling.
Bueno, creo que todos la necesitan.
Hey, look, man, I am not about to go talk to somebody I don't even know...
Hombre, no irי a hablar con alguien que ni siquiera conozco...
...about something that's none of their business.
...acerca de algo que no es asunto suyo.
All right. Catherine does need to respect you.
Claro. Catherine necesita respetarte.
But just remember, a woman's like a rose.
Pero recuerda que una mujer es como una rosa.
If you treat her right, she'll bloom.
Si la tratas bien florecerב.
If you don't, she'll wilt.
Si no, no lo harב.
Where'd you get that?
De dףnde sacaste eso?
Counseling.
De la terapia.
Great.
Estupendo.
What are you doing?
Quי haces?
I see you left me no pizza.
Veo que no me dejaste pizza.
I just lit that candle. I like the way it smells.
Enciende la vela. Me gusta como huele.
Well, I don't. Did you leave me any dinner at all?
A mם no. Me dejaste algo de comer?
I assumed you were eating with Michael.
Asumם que comerםas con Michael.
Does it not occur to you...
No se te ocurriף...
...that two people in this house both need to eat?
...que dos personas en esta casa necesitan comer?
You know what? If you would communicate with me...
Sabes quי? Si te comunicaras conmigo...
...maybe I could have something for you.
...quizבs tendrםa algo para ti.
Why do you have to make everything so difficult?
Por quי tienes que hacerlo todo tan difםcil?
Oh, I'm making everything difficult?
Yo lo hago difםcil?
I'm carrying the weight around here while you're off doing your own thing.
Yo cargo con todo mientras tת sales a ocuparte de tus cosas.
Excuse me?
Disculpa?
I'm working to pay this mortgage, and I pay for both of the cars.
Trabajo para pagar la hipoteca, pago los dos autos.
Yeah, and that's all you do. I pay all of our bills with my salary.
Sם, es todo lo que haces. Yo pago todas nuestras cuentas con mi sueldo.
Which you agreed to do. That's fair.
Lo que acordamos, lo justo.
Do you not like this house? Do you not like your car?
No te gusta esta casa? No te gusta tu auto?
Caleb, who takes care of this house?
Quiיn se ocupa de esta casa, Caleb?
Me. Who washes all the clothes?
Yo. Quiיn lava la ropa?
Me. Who gets all the groceries?
Yo. Quiיn compra la comida?
Me. Not to mention I'm helping my parents every weekend.
Yo. Sin contar que ayudo a mis padres los fines de semana.
I've got all this pressure on me.
Tengo toda esa presiףn.
The only thing you do for anybody is for yourself.
Lo תnico que haces por alguien es para ti mismo.
Let me tell you, you don't know the first thing about pressure.
Te dirי que ni siquiera sabes lo que es la presiףn.
All right? You think I put out house fires for myself?
Entiendes? Crees que yo enciendo esos fuegos para mם?
Or rush to car wrecks at 2 a.m. for myself?
O que salgo corriendo tras accidentes de autos por mם?
Or pull a child's body out of a lake for myself?
O rescato el cuerpo de un niסo en el lago para mם?
You have no idea what I go through.
No tienes idea de lo que tengo que pasar.
Yeah, but what do you do around here other than watch TV...
Sם. Pero quי haces cuando estבs aquם excepto ver TV...
...and waste time on the Internet?
...y perder el tiempo en Internet?
If looking at that trash is how you get fulfilled, that's fine.
Si ver esa basura es lo que te llena pues muy bien.
But I will not compete with it.
Pero no competirי con eso.
Well, I sure don't get it from you.
De seguro no lo obtendrי de ti.
And you won't.
No lo obtendrבs.
Because you care more about saving for your stupid boat...
Porque te interesa mבs ahorrar para tu estתpido barco...
...and pleasing yourself than you ever did about me.
...y complaciיndote a ti mismo de lo que te interesas en mם.
Shut up! I'm sick of you!
¡Cבllate! ¡Estoy harto de ti!
You disrespectful, ungrateful, selfish woman!
¡Irrespetuosa, malagradecida, y egoםsta!
- I'm not selfish. - How dare you say that?
- No soy egoםsta. - Cףmo te atreves a decir eso?
You constantly nag me and you drain the life out of me!
¡Me fastidias constantemente, me estבs succionando la vida!
I'm tired of it!
¡Estoy cansado de eso!
If you can't give me the respect I deserve...
Si no puedes darme el respeto que merezco...
Look at me!
¡Mםrame!
- then what's the point of this marriage?
...entonces cuבl es el punto de esta matrimonio?
I want out.
Quiero salirme de יl.
I just want out.
Simplemente salirme.
If you want out, that's fine with me!
¡Si eso quieres por mם estב bien!
Mr. Rudolph.
Sr. Rudolph.
Caleb.
Caleb.
- That's it. - All right.
- Se acabף - Estב bien.
Think we got it. We're good to go.
Lo tenemos, listo para irnos.
I think I got this.
Creo que lo entiendo.
- You think you know the truck? - Yeah.
- Crees que conoces el camiףn? - Sם.
All right. I'll tell you what.
Muy bien, te dirי algo.
We're gonna go inside and get something to drink.
Entraremos a buscar algo de tomar.
You bring me a hose stretcher.
Trבeme la malla.
All right.
Muy bien.
- That's mean, man. - No, it's good for him.
- Eso fue agresivo. - No, es bueno para יl
- Mother's gifts. - Okay.
- Regalos de madre. - Bien.
- And... - You know what? I forgot to tell you.
- Y... - Sabes quי? Olvidי decirte.
- I got Friday off and I'll be there. - Good.
- Libro el viernes y allם estarי. - Que bueno.
You know I ain't gonna let my son down.
Sabes que no defraudarי a mi hijo.
I know you won't.
Sי que no.
Hey, we still got that hot date tomorrow, right?
Todavםa tienes esa cita caliente maסana, no?
Oh, so now it's a hot date?
Ahora es una cita caliente?
Life's too short to have any other kind.
La vida es demasiado corta para citas de otro tipo.
You're right.
Tienes razףn.
- I love you, baby. - I love you too.
- Te quiero, amor. - Yo tambiיn.
- And I will see you in the morning. - All right.
- Te verי en la maסana. - Estב bien.
- Back home. - All right, see you later.
- De vuelta a casa. - Exacto, nos vemos.
Eric, what are you doing?
Quי estבs haciendo, Eric?
Wayne told me to grab a hose stretcher.
Me dijo que buscara la malla.
- A hose stretcher? - Yes, sir.
- La malla? - Sם, seסor.
Eric, you are the hose stretcher.
Eric, ese eres tת.
Man.
Hombre.
Honey, I agree with you. You gotta get out.
Querida, estoy de acuerdo. Tienes que terminarlo.
- He don't deserve you. - You can say that again.
- ֹl no te merece. - Dםmelo otra vez.
A real man's gotta be a hero to his wife before anybody, or he ain't a real man.
Un hombre es el hיroe de su esposa primero o no es hombre.
Do you need a place to stay? I can't imagine living in the same house.
Necesitas donde quedarte? No los imagino en la misma casa.
No, I decided that I'm not the one that's leaving.
No, decidם que no serי yo la que se vaya.
- He's the problem, not me. - That's right, girl. Stand your ground.
- ֹl es el problema, no yo. - Muy bien. Defiende tu territorio.
Make him respect you.
Haz que te respete.
If there's one thing a man understands...
Si hay algo que un hombre entiende es respeto.
It's respect. That's the issue. That's the reason our marriage is failing.
Ese es el problema. Por eso falla nuestro matrimonio.
She shows me no respect at all. And the saddest part about it is...
Ella no me respeta. Y lo mבs triste de eso...
He doesn't have a clue.
Es que יl ni se imagina.
He thinks our marriage has been fine for the most part.
Cree que nuestro matrimonio ha sido bueno en su mayor parte.
You know, he probably thinks...
Probablemente cree...
Our marriage has been fine until this year.
Nuestro matrimonio ha sido bueno hasta este aסo...
Now, all of a sudden, she goes off the deep end.
Ahora de repente, ella se pone dramבtica.
Do you think this happened all of a sudden?
Crees que eso pasa de repente?
I don't know what to think. I don't understand her.
No sי que pensar. No la entiendo.
She's emotional about everything.
Estב susceptible por todo.
She's easily offended and way too sensitive.
Se ofende fבcilmente y estב demasiado sensible.
I mean, he's so insensitive, you know?
ֹl es tan insensible, sabes?
He doesn't truly care how I feel. He doesn't listen to me.
No le importa como me siento. ֹl no me escucha.
Even if I say it over and over and over again.
Aunque se lo repita una y otra vez.
And then she starts nagging me and saying I don't listen to her...
Y luego empieza a fastidiarme y a decir que no la escucho...
...or something like that.
...o algo asם.
It drives me crazy. I feel like I'm going...
Me desquicia. Siento como si me volviera...
Insane.
Demente.
You know, he doesn't understand my needs.
ֹl no comprende mis necesidades.
I feel like we are completely and totally...
Siento que somos total y completamente...
Incompatible.
Incompatibles.
She's probably whining to her friends, making me sound like a criminal.
Debe estar llorando con sus amigas dejבndome como un criminal.
I can see them all right now, crying, having some sort of group hug.
Puedo verlas, llorando, abrazבndose.
It's gonna be okay, sweetie. It's gonna be all right.
Todo saldrב bien, querida. Todo saldrב bien.
You'll get through this.
Lo superarבs.
We have your back.
Estamos contigo.
Whatever you need.
Para lo que necesites.
So you think it's past the point of no return?
Crees que lleguי al punto de no retorno?
I don't have a reason to return.
No tengo razףn para el retorno.
- Bethany. - Hey, Kyle. Hey, Ross.
- Bethany. - Hola, Kyle. Hola, Ross.
- What's going on? - What are y'all doing?
- Quי pasa? - Quי estבn haciendo?
We're heading to the pizza barn to meet friends.
Vamos a la pizzerםa a encontrarnos con unas amigas.
Y'all wanna come?
Quieres venir?
Sure.
Claro.
Hey, we'll race you there. And if you win, we'll buy.
Hagamos una carrera. Si ganas nosotros pagamos.
Ready, set...
En sus marcas, listos...
Go, go, go.
Fuera.
Hey, Dad.
Hola, papב.
No, not really.
No creo.
I think Catherine and I are done.
Creo que Catherine se cansף.
No, it's over.
No, se terminף.
She said she wants out.
Dijo que querםa separarse.
Sure, yeah, you can come over tomorrow. I'll be home.
Claro que puedes venir maסana. Estarי en casa.
Dad, I gotta go.
Papב, me tengo que ir.
Public Safety to Engine 1, Battalion 1.
Seguridad Pתblica a Motor 1, Batallףn 1.
Respond to the intersection of Roosevelt and Kelley, 10-50-I rescue.
Responda a la intersecciףn de Roosevelt y Kelley 10-50 rescate.
- Time out, 12:21. - Hey, that's close by.
- Tiempo fuera, 12:21. - Oye, estuvo cerca.
Lieutenant, you and Terrell take the other truck and go with us.
Teniente, usted y Terrell busquen el otro camiףn y vengan.
Okay, let's roll.
Nos vamos.
Engine 1 is en route to Roosevelt and Kelley, 10-50 rescue.
Motor uno en ruta. A Roosevelt y Kelley, 10-50 rescate.
10-4, Engine 1.
10-4, Motor 1.
Lieutenant, you and Sanders have the Hurst tools ready if we need them.
Teniente, usted y Sanders tengan las herramientas Hurst listas.
- You stay with me when we pull up. - Yes, sir.
- Quיdate conmigo cuando subamos. - Sם, seסor.
We've already got a crowd.
Ya tenemos una multitud...
- Can you see it? - We've got one car on the tracks.
- La ves? - Hay un auto en las vםas.
You're kidding me.
Es chiste.
Oh, it doesn't look good.
No se ve bien.
Engine 1, it's 10-23.
Motor 1, es 10-23.
We have a two-vehicle accident with possible entrapment.
Tenemos un choque de dos vehםculos y gente atrapada.
One of the vehicles is on the train tracks.
Uno de los vehםculos estב en los rieles del tren.
Notify the train dispatcher to stop all trains in progress.
Avםsenle al despachador de trenes que paralice la actividad.
Ten-four, Command. Be advised, EMS is en route.
10-4, Comando. Tengan en cuenta que, EMS estב en camino.
- Rookie, you come with me. - Yes, sir. Let's go, guys.
- Novato, ven conmigo. - Sם, seסor. Vamos muchachos.
You two go check out the car. Let me know what you got.
Ustedes dos revisen el auto. Dםganme lo que encuentren.
I need an inch-and-three-quarter line.
Necesito una lםnea de 69 cm.
Harmon, you check out the passenger.
Harmon, asiste al pasajero.
All right, I need you all to stay clear of the tracks and the vehicle.
Quiero que despejen las vםas y del vehםculo...
I'm Captain Holt from the Fire Department.
Soy el capitבn Holt del Departamento de Bomberos.
- We're here to help. - Help me, please. I can't get out.
- Vinimos a ayudarlos. - Ayתdeme. No puedo salir.
- Where are you hurting? - My legs are hurting.
- Siente dolor? - Me duelen las piernas.
- Please, please help me. - All right, we're gonna help you.
- Por favor, ayתdeme. - Vamos a ayudarlo.
Okay. Where else are you hurting?
Quי mבs le duele?
My neck is hurting. Please, please help.
El cuello. Ayתdenme por favor.
We're gonna get you out of here. You're gonna be fine.
Saldrב de aquם. Estarב bien.
Please don't leave me. Please don't let me die.
No me dejen. No me dejen morir.
I promise you I am not going to leave you.
Le prometo que no lo dejaremos.
- You're gonna be all right. - Captain.
- Estarב bien. - Capitבn.
- She's alive but not responding. - Get the spreaders.
- Estב viva pero no responde. - Traigan las herramientas.
Those two will be okay. They've got minor injuries.
Estos dos estarבn bien. Tienen heridas menores
We have to cut these two out. Sanders, help Harmon.
Habrב que cortar para sacar a estos dos. Sanders, ayuda a Harmon.
- I need you to check for gas leaks. - Yes, sir.
- Revisa si hay goteo de gasolina. - Sם, seסor.
We've got an ambulance coming.
Una ambulancia estב en camino.
- I'm gonna stay right here with you. - Okay.
- Voy a quedarme con usted. - Estב bien.
You're gonna hear a very loud noise.
Oirב un ruido muy fuerte.
That just means we're getting you out faster.
Eso significa que lo sacaremos mבs rבpidamente.
- All right. You're gonna be all right. - Okay.
- Estarב bien. - Sם.
- Captain, did I just hear a train? - Guys, there's a train coming.
- Eso es un tren, Capitבn? - Muchachos, viene un tren.
Dispatcher, this is Roosevelt Command.
Despachador aquם el comando Roosevelt.
We have a car on the train tracks.
Hay un auto en los rieles.
Notify the train dispatcher to stop all trains in progress.
Avise al despachador que detenga los trenes en movimiento.
Roosevelt Command, be advised...
Comando Roosevelt alerta.
... we are currently unable to make contact with the train dispatcher.
...no podemos hacer contacto con el despachador de trenes.
No, no, no. We don't have time.
No, no, no. No tenemos tiempo.
Come on, we're gonna have to push it out of the way. Let's go, let's go.
Hay que empujarlo fuera de la vםa. Vamos, vamos.
No, I don't wanna die. I don't wanna die.
No quiero morir. No quiero morir.
All right, let's go. Push. Push.
Muy bien, vamos, empujen.
Captain, it's not rolling. We gotta drag it off.
Capitבn, no rueda, hay que halarlo.
- Get the chain. - Hey, Wayne, hook up the chain.
- Busquen la cadena. - Wayne, engancha la cadena.
Hook up the chain.
Engancha la cadena.
Hey, there's a train!
¡Viene el tren!
- Captain, we gotta pick this up. - All right, grab the front.
- Capitבn, hay que izarlo. - Muy bien, engancha el frente.
Lift on three. One, two, three.
Eleven en tres. Un, dos, tres.
Again. One, two, three.
Otra vez. Un, dos, tres.
Again. Let's go. We're getting this car off the tracks.
Otra vez, vamos. Sacaremos el auto de las vםas.
One, two, three.
Un, dos, tres.
Again. One, two, three.
Otra vez. Un, dos, tres.
- Again, captain. - One, two, three.
- Otra vez, Capitבn. - Un, dos, tres.
One, two, three.
Un, dos, tres.
Harmon, go back and get the spreaders.
Harmon, busca las herramientas atrבs.
Medic!
¡Mיdicos!
- You all right? - Come on, let's go.
- Estב bien? - Venga, vamos.
You'll be okay. You're gonna be all right.
Estarב bien. Estarב bien.
Thank you, Lord.
Gracias, Seסor.
Thank you, God.
Gracias, Dios.
Are you okay?
Estבn bien?
Captain, I just needed a minute.
Capitבn, necesito un minuto.
Well, I broke my record of how close I could come to death and still live.
Rompם mi record de lo cerca que he estado de morir.
Well, don't break it next time.
No lo rompas la prףxima vez.
I wasn't trying to break it this time.
No trataba de hacerlo esta.
Hey.
Hola.
Don't tell my wife.
No le digas a mi esposa.
- Hey, lieutenant? - Yeah?
- Teniente? - Sם?
This kind of thing doesn't happen all the time, does it?
Esto no pasa siempre, o sם?
Risking our lives? Yes.
Arriesgar nuestras vidas? Sם, sם pasa.
Playing chicken with a train? First time.
Jugar gallina con un tren? Primera vez.
- Aren't you afraid of dying? - No.
- No le da miedo morir? - No.
Because I know where I'm going.
Porque se adonde irי.
I just don't wanna get there because I got hit by a train.
Solo que no quiero llegar porque me atropellף un tren.
Why don't you come help me work on some dinner?
Por quי no me ayudas con la cena?
All right.
Muy bien.
Hey, captain, hold on for a second.
Capitבn, espere un segundo.
You know where you're going?
Sabe a donde irב?
- I'm going to my office. - No.
- A mi oficina. - No.
You believe in heaven and hell?
Cree en el cielo y el infierno?
I don't know.
No lo sי.
When I die, I'm going in the ground. That's where I'm staying.
Cuando me muera me enterrarבn. Ahם me quedarי.
You know, you and Michael both seem so sure, but one of you is wrong.
Usted y Michel parecen muy seguros pero se equivocan.
It ain't me.
No soy yo.
How do you know?
Cףmo lo sabes?
Hey, listen, you might not agree with Michael...
Escucha, puedes no estar de acuerdo con Michael...
...but you and I both know he's the real deal.
...pero tת y yo sabemos que יl es el hombre.
Son, how long has this been going on?
Hijo, cuבnto llevas en esto?
I don't know, Dad. We've had our arguments now and then...
No sי, papב. Hemos peleado una que otra vez...
...but it seems like now she is constantly frustrated with me.
...pero ahora parece que ella estב frustrada conmigo.
I mean, I walk in the door and she's mad about something.
Entro por la puerta y ya estב enojada por algo.
Have you given her reason to be upset?
Le has dado razones para enojarse?
I've never known Catherine to be unreasonable.
Nunca he creםdo que Catherine sea irracional.
I could have saved the lives of two people at work...
Puedo haber salvado dos vidas en el trabajo pero si no...
...and if I'm not here helping wash the dishes, I'm a horrible husband.
...lavo los platos entonces soy un esposo terrible.
But, Caleb, she needs your help here as well.
Pero, Caleb, ella tambiיn necesita tu ayuda aquם.
Doesn't she help her parents out every week?
No ayuda a sus padres cada semana?
- She can't do everything around here. - You sound like you're taking her side.
- No puede hacer todo aquם. - Parece que estבs de su lado.
But she's working and she's trying...
Pero ella estב trabajando y tratando...
Mom, I do not need you to tell me I'm doing everything wrong.
Mamב no necesito que me digas que lo hago todo mal.
I've got Catherine for that. I am not the problem, she is.
Para eso tengo a Catherine. Yo no soy el problema, es ella.
- All I'm saying is, if she's working... - Cheryl, let's hear Caleb out.
- Solo digo que si trabaja... - Cheryl, escuchemos a Caleb.
I wanna know what's going on with him.
Quiero saber quי le pasa.
Dad, can I please have a few minutes to talk with you, alone?
Papב, podemos hablar a solas por unos minutos?
Caleb, I just wanna help you and Catherine.
Caleb, solo quiero ayudarlos a ti y a Catherine.
- Dad. - Honey.
- Papב. - Amor.
Why don't you let us take a walk? It's all right.
Por quי no nos dejas dar un paseo?
Okay.
Estב bien.
Dad, why did you have to bring her?
Papב por quי tenםas que traerla?
Caleb, because she's my wife.
Porque es mi esposa, Caleb.
And your mother, no one loves you more than her.
Y tu madre, nadie te quiere mבs que ella.
She just... She's always fixing me.
Ella siempre trata de arreglarme.
She's still trying to fix me. I'm not broken.
Todavםa trata de arreglarme a mם. Y no estoy roto.
Son, if you're looking for a perfect mother...
Hijo, si buscas a la mamב perfecta...
...l'm afraid there's not one out there.
...Me temo que no existe.
But she's a good woman.
Pero ella es una buena mujer.
And I love her now more than I ever have.
Y la amo mבs ahora que nunca antes.
I'm not saying I don't love her, Dad. Just that she...
No digo que no la quiera, papב Es que ella...
She grates on me.
Ella me crispa.
Have you not seen a change in her in the last two years?
No has visto un cambio en ella desde hace dos aסos?
Yeah, she treats you better.
Sם, te trata mejor.
But you've also put up with a lot over the years.
Pero tambiיn has aguantado mucho estos aסos.
Well, so has she.
Y ella tambiיn.
Dad, I'm glad you didn't split up...
Papב me alegra que no se hayan separado...
...but I would have understood if you had.
...pero yo hubiera entendido que lo hicieran.
Do you know why we didn't?
Sabes por quי no lo hicimos?
Not really. She realized she couldn't do any better?
No. Por quי ella se dio cuenta de que no encontrarםa algo mejor?
Not quite.
No.
Caleb, the Lord did a work in us.
Caleb, el Seסor trabajo con nosotros.
In both of us.
Con ambos.
The Lord?
El Seסor?
- You're giving credit to God? - Why does that bother you?
- Le das el crיdito al Seסor? - Por quי te molesta?
You've always believed in God.
Siempre has creםdo en Dios.
If there's a God out there, he's not interested in me and my problems.
Si existe no estב interesado en mis problemas.
I disagree. I'd say he's very interested.
No estoy de acuerdo. Creo que estב muy interesado.
Then where's he been in my life?
En quי ha estado en mi vida?
He's been at work all around you. You just haven't realized it.
Ha trabajado contigo, solo que tת no lo ves.
You haven't exactly given him an open invitation.
No lo has invitado.
What is this place?
Quי es este lugar?
Used to be a summer camp across the lake.
Era un campamento de verano sobre el lago.
I think this must be a part of it.
Creo que esto debe ser una parte.
Son, I used to be where you are right now.
Hijo, estuve en tu posiciףn.
God didn't matter to me.
Dios no me importaba.
But I can't say that anymore.
Pero ya no puedo decir eso.
I never understood why Jesus had to die on the cross...
Nunca entendם por que Jesתs tuvo que morir en la cruz...
Dad, please.
Papב, por favor.
We had this conversation last month.
Tuvimos esta charla hace un mes.
I'm glad this new faith is working for you and Mom, I really am.
Estoy contento de que la fe les funcione a mamב y a ti.
It's just...
Simplemente...
It's not for me.
No es para mם.
Caleb...
Caleb...
...is there anything in you that wants to save your marriage?
...alguna parte de ti quiere salvar tu matrimonio?
Maybe. If Catherine wanted to, but she doesn't. She wants divorce.
Quizבs. Si Catherine quisiera, pero no quiere. Quiere el divorcio.
Is that what you want?
Eso es lo que tת crees?
I want peace.
Quiero paz.
But what difference does it make?
Pero quי importa eso?
She signs the papers, Dad, it's all over.
Ella firma los papeles, papב. Se acabף.
Have you agreed to start the process with her?
Aceptaste empezar el proceso con ella?
No, but I think we both understand where this is all headed.
No, pero creo que ambos sabemos a lo que vamos.
I've got plans to meet with my lawyer tomorrow.
Voy a reunirme con mi abogado maסana.
Caleb, I want you to do something for me.
Caleb, quiero que hagas algo por mם.
What?
Quי?
I want you to hold off on the divorce for 40 days.
Quiero que pospongas el divorcio por 40 dםas.
Why?
Por quי?
I'm gonna send you something in the mail.
Te mandarי algo por correo.
Something that'll take you that long to do.
Algo que te tomarב ese tiempo.
- What is it? - It's what saved our marriage.
- Quי es? - Lo que salvף nuestro matrimonio.
Dad, if this is a religious thing, I'd rather you didn't.
Papב, si es algo religioso prefiero que no.
Look at it as a gift from your father.
Mםralo como un regalo de tu padre.
Take one day at a time, then see what happens.
Vive un dםa a la vez a ver que pasa.
Please, son. If for no other reason, do it for me.
Por favor, hijo. Si no por otra razףn, hazlo por mם.
I'm asking as your father.
Te lo pido como padre.
- Forty days? - Forty days.
- Cuarenta dםas?
- Eating alone? - Well, hello, Dr. Keller.
- Comiendo sola? - Hola, Dr. Keller.
- Gavin. - Gavin, sorry.
- Gavin. - Gavin, disculpa.
- How are you? - I'm doing well.
- Cףmo estבs? - Me va bien
I just need a place to put my plate down.
Necesitaba un lugar donde poner mi plato.
Is this spot reserved?
Estב reservado?
Deidra was supposed to meet me, but you're welcome to join us.
Deidra iba a comer conmigo, pero bienvenido.
Well, if you're gonna twist my arm, I don't want any trouble.
Bueno, si me convences no quiero problemas.
Are you gonna eat wearing your clean white coat?
Va a comer con su bata?
I need to keep up with the latest fashions.
Tengo que estar a la תltima moda.
It seems all the doctors are wearing one these days.
Parece que todos los doctores la estבn usando.
But it's probably not too smart while I'm eating.
Pero posiblemente no sea elegante mientras como.
I didn't know doctors cared about fashion.
No sabםa que a los doctores les interesara la moda.
We keep up with the attractive fashions...
Seguimos la moda que...
...the Public Relations employees wear.
...los empleados de relaciones pתblicas usan.
I see.
Ya veo.
Since there's only one person in that category...
Como solamente hay alguien en esa categorםa...
...l'm sure she'd feel honored.
...Seguramente ella se siente honrada.
She should. She's pretty amazing.
Deberםa, ella es increםble.
Hey, you look good.
Oye, te ves bien.
Thanks. I try to take care of myself.
Gracias, trato de cuidarme.
You like this song?
Te gusta esta canciףn?
Oh, yeah.
Sם.
You feel that?
Lo sientes?
It's called chemistry, and we got it.
Se llama quםmica y hay entre tת y yo.
Wayne won't leave you.
Wayne no te dejarב.
- Hey, man, you seen my bag in here? - No, I ain't seen it.
- Has visto mi bulto? - No, no lo he visto.
All right. It's probably in my locker.
Seguramente estב en mi armario.
Where were we?
Dףnde estבbamos?
Oh, come on. That ain't funny.
Vamos, no es gracioso.
This ain't no show.
Esto no es un programa.
This is me-time.
Es mi hora.
Terrell!
¡Terrell!
Wayne.
Wayne.
Forty days? Does Catherine know?
Cuarenta dםas? Catherine sabe?
I'm not gonna tell her.
No se lo dirי.
If she wants to go ahead and file, that's up to her.
Si quiere poner la demanda, es su elecciףn.
Divorce is a hard thing, man.
El divorcio es duro.
Well, if it brings peace...
Si me trae paz...
But, Caleb, you want the right kind of peace.
Pero Caleb, tu quieres verdadera paz.
What do you mean by that?
Quי quieres decir?
You know what that ring on your finger means?
Sabes quי significa el anillo en tu dedo?
- Means I'm married. - Yeah.
- Que estoy casado. - Sם.
It also means you made a lifelong covenant.
Tambiיn que hiciste un compromiso de por vida.
You putting on that ring while saying your vows.
Te pusiste ese anillo mientras hacםas tus votos.
The sad part about it is...
Lo triste de eso es que...
...when most people promise for better or worse...
...cuando la gente dice para bien o para mal...
...they really only mean for the better.
...solamente lo dicen para bien.
Catherine and I were in love when we got married, but today...
Catherine y yo estבbamos enamorados cuando nos casamos.
...we're two very different people, all right?
Pero hoy somos personas diferentes, no?
It's just not working out anymore.
Ya no funciona.
Caleb, salt and pepper are completely different.
Caleb, la sal y la pimienta son completamente diferentes.
Their makeup is different, their taste and their color.
La preparaciףn, el gusto, el color.
But you always see them together.
Pero siempre van juntas.
And when you...
Y cuando tת...
Hold on just a second.
Espera un segundo.
What are you doing?
Quי hacen?
Michael. Hey.
Hey Michael.
What'd you do that for?
Por quי lo harםan?
Caleb, when two people get married, it's for better or for worse.
Caleb, cuando dos personas se casan es para bien o para mal.
For richer or for poorer.
En la riqueza y la pobreza.
In sickness and in health.
En la salud y la enfermedad.
I know that.
Ya lo sי.
But marriages aren't fireproof. Sometimes, you get burned.
Pero el matrimonio no es a prueba de fuego, a veces te quemas.
Fireproof doesn't mean that a fire will never come...
A prueba de fuego no quiere decir que el fuego no llegarב...
...but that when it comes, you'll be able to withstand it.
...quiere decir que cuando venga estarבs listo para enfrentarlo.
- You didn't have to glue them. - Don't do it, Caleb.
- No hay que pegarlo. - No lo hagas, Caleb.
If you pull them apart now, you'll break either one or both of them.
Si los separas ahora, romperבs alguno o a los dos.
I am not a perfect person, but better than most.
No soy perfecto, pero soy mejor que muchos.
And if my marriage is failing, it is not all my fault.
Si mi matrimonio estב fallando no es por mם.
But, Caleb, I've seen you run into a burning building...
Pero Caleb, te he visto corriendo hacia un edificio...
...to save people you don't even know.
...para salvar gente que ni conoces.
But you're gonna let your own marriage just burn to the ground.
Pero dejarבs que tu matrimonio se queme.
Michael, you are my friend.
Michael, tת eres mi amigo.
And I have allowed you to speak freely with me on this job.
Y te he permitido hablarme con libertad en el trabajo.
Don't abuse it.
No abuses.
My son, this 40-day journey cannot be taken lightly.
Hijo, este viaje de 40 dםas no puede ser tomado a la ligera.
It is a challenging and often difficult process...
Es un complejo y retador proceso...
... but an incredibly fulfilling one.
...pero increםblemente satisfactorio.
If you will commit to a day at a time for 40 days...
Si te comprometes a vivir un dםa a la vez por 40 dםas...
... the results could change your life and your marriage.
...los resultados pueden cambiar tu vida y tu matrimonio.
Consider it a dare from others who have done it before you.
Considיralo un reto que los que ya lo han hecho te estבn poniendo.
Day one: The first part of this dare is fairly simple.
Dםa uno: La primera parte del reto es bastante simple.
Although love is communicated in a number of ways...
Aunque el amor se comunica de muchas maneras...
... our words often reflect the condition of our heart.
...las palabras a menudo reflejan lo que hay en el corazףn.
For the next day...
Durante el siguiente dםa...
... resolve to say nothing negative to your spouse at all.
...decםdete a no decirle nada negativo a tu esposa.
If the temptation arises, choose not to say anything.
Si sientes la tentaciףn, no digas nada.
It's better to hold your tongue than to say something you'll regret.
Es mejor callarse que decir algo de lo que te arrepientas.
Be quick to listen, slow to speak and slow to get angry.
Se rבpido para escuchar, lento para hablar y para enojarte.
James 1: 19.
Santiago 1: 19.
Would you have time to take that to the dry-cleaners today?
Podrםas ir a la tintorerםa?
Think after two days off, you would have already taken care of that.
Despuיs de dos dםas habrבs mejorado mucho.
Day two:
Dםa dos:
It is difficult to demonstrate love when you feel little to no motivation.
Es difםcil demostrar amor cuando sientes poca o ninguna motivaciףn.
But love in its truest sense is not based on feelings...
Pero el amor no estב basado en los sentimientos...
... but a determination to show thoughtful actions...
...sino en la decisiףn de hacer actos considerados...
... even when there seems to be no reward.
...aunque parezca que no haya recompensa.
In addition to saying nothing negative to your spouse today...
Sumado a no decirle nada negativo a tu esposa...
... do at least one unexpected gesture as an act of kindness.
...ten aunque sea un gesto de generosidad.
I poured your coffee.
Te servם cafי.
I don't have time for coffee.
No tengo tiempo.
Day three:
Dםa tres:
Whatever you put your time, energy and money into...
En lo que inviertas tu tiempo, energםa y dinero...
... will become more important to you.
...se volverב lo mבs importante para ti.
It's hard to care for something you're not investing in.
Es difםcil preocuparse por algo en lo que no inviertes nada.
Along with refraining from any negative comments...
Ademבs de no hacer comentarios negativos...
... buy your wife something that says you were thinking of her today.
...cףmprale algo a tu esposa que le diga que pensaste en ella.
Yeah, I need to order some flowers or something for my wife.
Sם, quiero ordenar flores o algo asם para mi esposa.
No. No, it doesn't matter.
No, no importa.
Sure. How much does that cost?
Claro. Cuבnto cuestan?
Forty-five? Do you have something cheaper?
Cuarenta y cinco? Tiene algo mבs barato?
Yeah, yeah, that's more like it. Let's go with the 25.
Sם, eso estב mejor, que sean 25.
How about a box of chocolates or something?
Y chocolates?
How much is that?
Cuבnto?
You're killing me.
Me estב matando.
That's better.
Mejor.
Okay, how about a little stuffed bear?
Y un osito de peluche?
All right, forget the bear.
Estב bien, olvide el oso.
How long is it gonna take you to throw something like that together?
Cuבnto se demorarבn en hacerlo?
Man, you done lost your mind.
Amigo, perdiste la cabeza.
Terrell, I can bench 300 right now.
Terrell, puedo hacer 300 ahora.
For real?
De verdad?
Why can't we all come to the same obvious conclusion?
Por quי no todos llegamos a la misma conclusiףn?
That I am the man.
Yo soy el hombre.
All I know is the man left the thermal-imaging device...
Solo sי que el hombre dejף el aparato de imבgenes termales...
...on the bumper of the truck last night.
...en el parachoques del camiףn anoche.
- That's an $8000 piece of equipment. - My bad, captain.
- Es un equipo de 800 dףlares. - Fue mi culpa, Capitבn.
That doesn't change the fact...
Eso no cambia el hecho de que...
...when it comes to difficult situations, I can take it.
...cuando hay dificultades yo estoy allם...
Man, I can't take this much ego.
No soporto tanto ego.
You've been bragging on yourself for 10 minutes, man.
Has estado fanfarroneando por diez minutos.
It ain't bragging if it's true.
No fanfarroneo, digo la verdad.
Last week at the apartment fire, I pulled off two attack lines...
La semana pasada en el fuego en el edificio, movם dos lםneas de ataque.
...laid my own supply line and caught a hydrant in two minutes.
Saquי mi propia lםnea y la conectי a un hidrante en dos minutos.
- Other folks could do that, man. - Not from this station.
- Otros pueden hacer eso. - No en esta estaciףn.
- Tom McBride could. - At Station 4?
- Tom McBride podrםa. - El de la Estaciףn 4?
He might do it in two and a half, but he can't do it under two.
Quizבs en dos minutos y medio pero no por debajo de dos.
- I don't know. - Captain...
- No sי. - Capitבn...
...he's strong, but he's not as fast.
...el es fuerte pero no rבpido.
I could take him any day of the week.
Le ganarםa de seguro.
Wayne, you seem pretty high on yourself.
Wayne, pareces muy seguro de ti mismo.
I think confidence is a good thing, but you're over the top.
Creo que la confianza es buena, pero tת exageras.
Man, he way over the top.
Exagera mucho...
I can back it up. That's all I'm saying.
Puedo hacerlo. Es lo תnico que digo.
Wrath of God, baby.
La ira de Dios.
- What's that for? - We're about to have a little contest.
- Quי es eso? - Haremos un pequeסo concurso.
We're just gonna see if Wayne really is the man.
Veremos si Wayne es el hombre.
That is, if he's for the challenge.
Si se atreve con un reto.
I'm all about this.
Estoy listo.
All right.
Muy bien.
I'll go first.
Yo primero.
- What are you gonna do? - Michael, time me.
- Quי harבs? - Michael, cuיntame el tiempo.
You got it. Ready?
Claro. Listo?
Go.
Ya.
No way.
No puede ser.
Man, you crazy.
Estבs loco.
He gonna drink the whole thing.
Se lo tomarב todo.
Twenty-three seconds.
23 segundos.
All right, man. You're up.
Muy bien, ahora tת.
All right. That was impressive.
Impresionante.
Till I do it under 20.
Hasta que yo lo haga en menos de 20.
- Time me. - Oh, I'll time you.
- Cuיntame el tiempo. - Estב bien.
- Ready? - Ladies.
- Listo? - Seסoras.
Go.
Ya.
- Come on, Wayne. - It's hot.
- Vamos, Wayne. - Estב caliente.
- Go, Wayne. - That's it, Wayne.
- Ya basta, Wayne.
How about you take it?
Y si lo tomas?
- You gotta drink that, bro. - Fourteen seconds.
- Tienes que tomarlo. - Catorce segundos.
- Come on. - It burns!
- Vamos. - ¡Quema!
Where the man at now, huh?
Dףnde estב el hombre ahora?
I thought he said he could take it.
Creo que dijo que podםa.
My mouth's on fire!
¡Se me quema la boca!
Captain, how'd you do that, man?
Capitבn, cףmo haces eso?
You could do it too, Terrell...
Tת podrםas tambiיn Terrel...
...if you replaced yours with tomato juice.
...si sustituyeras el tuyo con jugo de tomate.
That is classic. That was awesome.
Un clבsico, increםble.
Dr. Anderson?
Dr. Anderson?
Wanted to remind you about your interview in 10 minutes.
Querםa recordarle su entrevista en diez minutos.
Catherine, thank you. I'll be there.
Catherine, gracias. Ahם estarי.
Congratulations on your cancer-research award.
Felicitaciones por su premio a la investigaciףn del cבncer.
- You deserve it. - I appreciate that.
- Se lo merece. - Se lo agradezco.
This is Catherine.
Ella es Catherine.
Hey, it's Caleb. I wanted to call and check on you.
Hola es Caleb. Quise llamarte a ver como estabas.
You wanted to check on me? What for?
Ver como estaba? Para quי?
You know, just see if you needed anything.
Por si acaso necesitabas algo.
You called to see if I needed anything?
Llamaste para ver si necesitaba algo?
Right, yeah. You want me to bring something home for you...
Sם, necesitas que lleve algo a casa?
... or get something from the store in the morning?
O que busque algo por la maסana?
Caleb, you never asked me this before. What's going on?
Caleb, nunca habםas preguntado eso. Quי pasa?
I just wanted to see if you needed anything, that's it.
Solo querםa saber si necesitabas algo.
I'm fine.
Estoy bien.
Okay.
Que bueno.
All right, well...
Bueno, entonces...
...goodbye.
...adiףs.
Day four, done.
Dםa cuatro, listo.
Hey, Cat, how you doing, girl?
Hola Cat, cףmo estבs?
Confused.
Confundida.
- My husband's acting weird. - What's he doing?
- Mi esposo estב raro. - Quי hace?
Well, in the last few days...
En los תltimos dםas...
...he has fixed me coffee, bought me these pitiful little flowers...
...me ha hecho cafי, comprado estas pobre florecitas...
...and just now, called just to see if I'm doing okay.
...y ahora llamף para saber si estoy bien.
- Really? - Yeah.
- De verdad? - Sם.
I'll tell you what he's doing.
Te dirי lo que estב haciendo.
He's trying to butter you up for a divorce.
Trata de ablandarte por lo del divorcio.
And why would he do that?
Por quי lo harםa?
Before my cousin Luwanna got a divorce...
Antes de que mi prima Luwanna se divorciara...
...her husband did the same thing.
...su esposo hizo lo mismo.
He started acting nice and sweet, next thing we know...
Se puso todo dulce y tierno lo prףximo que supimos...
...he walks away with the house and most of their money.
...fue que se quedף con su casa y su dinero.
He hasn't even talked to her since. Don't you let him deceive you, girl.
Ni siquiera le ha vuelto a hablar. No dejes que te engaסe.
Did you clear your history?
Limpiaste el historial?
What?
Quי?
Did you wipe the websites off so nobody would see where you've been?
Borraste las pבginas web para que no sepa dףnde has estado?
You know, Caleb, you're not fooling anybody.
Caleb, no engaסas a nadie.
I know what you're trying to do...
No sי quי tratas de hacer...
...buying me flowers and calling me at work.
...mandבndome flores, llamבndome al trabajo.
And what is that?
Quי es esto?
I'm meeting with a lawyer next week, and don't you think...
Me reunirי con mi abogado la semana que viene y no creas...
...l'm buying into this nice-guy routine.
...que te creo esta rutina de niסo bueno.
What are you talking about?
De quי estבs hablando?
You're not getting one dime more than you deserve.
No tendrבs ni un centavo mבs de lo que mereces.
When this divorce is final, I'm taking my share.
Este divorcio es definitivo. Yo quiero mi parte.
- Is that what you think I'm doing? - No, I know that's what you're doing.
- Eso crees que hago? - No, sי que lo estבs haciendo.
Well, you're wrong.
Te equivocas.
You never assume I would do anything worthy of respect.
Nunca asumes que pueda hacer algo de valor o respetable...
- Anything honorable. - Honorable?
- Nada honorable. - Honorable?
Honorable? What were you just looking at, Caleb?
Honorable? Quי mirabas, Caleb?
What was on that computer screen? Was that honorable?
Quי habםa en la pantalla? Eso es honorable?
Who do you think you're fooling?
A quiיn quieres que engaסas?
Do you know why your sweet little gestures mean nothing to me?
No sabes que tus pequeסos gestos no significan nada para mם?
It's because that's the kind of man you've become.
Es por eso que te has convertido en el hombre que eres.
When you're alone, that's what you default to.
Es lo que haces cuando estבs solo.
And there is nothing honorable about it.
Y no tiene nada de honorable.
Mr. Rudolph.
Sr. Rudolph.
Caleb.
Caleb.
- Hello? - It's not working, Dad.
- Hola? - No estב funcionando, papב.
What's not working?
Quי no funciona?
This whole love dare thing. It is not working.
Lo del reto del amor. No funciona.
Tell me what's going on.
Cuיntame lo que pasa.
I have been doing everything that it says to do...
He hecho todo lo que dice...
...and she has completely rejected all of it.
...y ella lo ha rechazado completamente.
Caleb, this process takes 40 days, not four.
Caleb, este proceso toma 40 dםas no 4.
What's the point of going down a dead-end road...
Cuבl es el punto de seguir por un camino sin salida...
- ... when it's not going anywhere? - You don't know that yet.
...que no va a ningתn lado? - Todavםa no lo sabes.
Caleb, you're not a quitter.
Caleb, tת no eres de los que se rinden.
And something tells me you're doing just enough to get by.
Y algo me dices que haces apenas lo suficiente.
Am I right?
Estoy en lo correcto?
- I feel nothing. - I understand, son.
- No siento nada. - Te entiendo, hijo.
But this is not based on feelings.
Pero esto no se basa en sentimientos.
It's a decision.
Es una decisiףn.
You can't give up yet.
No puedes rendirte aתn.
Keep taking a day at a time.
Continתa viviendo un dםa a la vez.
Yes, sir.
Sם, seסor.
I love you, son.
Te quiero hijo.
You too, Dad.
Yo tambiיn, papב.
How is he?
Cףmo estב?
We've gotta start praying for him more.
Tendremos que seguir orando por יl.
Mama, I don't know what to do.
Mamב, no sי quי hacer.
I know you always told me to hang on during the hard times, but...
Sי que siempre me has dicho que aguante los tiempos malos.
You don't know what I've been competing with.
Pero no sabes con lo que estoy compitiendo.
I mean, when he look...
Es decir cuando me mira...
He makes me feel so humiliated.
...me hace sentir humillada.
And he doesn't even know it.
Y ni siquiera se da cuenta.
When did I stop being good enough for him?
Cuבndo deje de ser buena para יl?
So, what day are you on?
En quי dםa vas?
- Eighteen. - And?
- 18. - Y?
And it's still difficult.
Sigue siendo difםcil.
Every day has me adding a new concept to the way I treat her.
Cada dםa suma un nuevo concepto en mi forma de tratarla.
For example?
Por ejemplo?
Well, here.
Bueno, aquם.
Day 16 was about praying for her. I kind of skipped that one.
El dםa 16 tenםa que orar por ella. Pero me lo saltי.
Day 17 is about listening to her.
El dםa 17 era escucharla.
Eighteen's about studying her again.
El 18 estudiarla de nuevo.
- Studying her? - Yeah.
- Estudiarla? - Sם.
Here.
Aquם.
"When a man is trying to win the heart of a woman, he studies her.
"Cuando un hombre trata de conquistar una mujer la estudia.
He learns her likes, dislikes, habits and hobbies.
Aprende lo que le gusta, le disgusta, hבbitos y hobbies.
But after he wins her heart and marries her...
Pero cuando la conquista y se casa...
...he often stops learning about her.
...deja de aprender sobre ella.
If the amount he studied her before marriage...
Si la cantidad de estudio antes de casarse...
...was equal to a high school degree, he should continue to learn...
...equivaliera a la secundaria, deberםa seguir aprendiendo...
...until he gains a college degree, a master's degree...
...hasta que se gradתe en la universidad, haga una maestrםa...
...and ultimately, a doctorate degree.
...y finalmente un doctorado.
It is a lifelong journey that draws his heart ever closer to hers."
Es el viaje de una vida que lleva su corazףn mבs cerca al de ella. "
That's a pretty good concept. I never thought about it like that.
Es un buen concepto. Nunca lo habםa pensado asם.
So do you study Tina?
Tת sם estudias a Tina?
Yeah, but I don't think I got my college degree on her yet.
Sם, pero no creo tener mi tםtulo de la universidad sobre ella.
So tell me a little bit more about the studying her.
Cuיntame mבs de eso de estudiarla.
I'm supposed to make her a candlelight dinner...
Tengo que prepararle una cena con velas...
...and then ask her a whole list of questions.
...y hacerle una lista de preguntas.
Well, my advice is go all out.
Bueno, mi consejo es que lo hagas a lo grande.
Meaning?
Significa?
Don't go cheap. If you don't cook, get it from a good restaurant.
No seas tacaסo. Si no cocinas, encarga a un buen restaurante.
Take it home, use your best dishes, glasses, music, everything.
Lleva la comida a tu casa, usa tus mejores platos, copas, mתsica.
Make it a memorable date.
Has algo memorable.
Man, what you talking about?
De quי estבs hablando?
- You ain't had a date in a year. - I'm like a fine wine.
- No has tenido citas en un aסo. - Soy como el buen vino.
I need about 35 years to reach perfection.
Necesito 35 aסos para alcanzar la perfecciףn.
But the lady that gets Wayne Floyd, she'll get the complete package.
Pero la que se quede con Wayne Floyd, tendrב el paquete completo.
- You mean complete wreckage. - No.
- El desastre completo. - No.
I'm 255 pounds of pure love.
Soy 116 kilos de puro amor.
All you need to make marriage work is a little bit of romance.
Todo lo que se necesita para que un matrimonio funcione es romance.
And that comes from right here.
Y eso viene de aquם.
Man, that's easy to say when you ain't never been married.
Es fבcil decirlo cuando no has estado casado nunca.
It's a lot harder than you think.
Es mucho mבs duro de lo que crees.
One day I'm gonna walk in with a tanned beauty on my arm.
Un dםa entrarי con una belleza del brazo.
I'll show you how easy it can be.
Te mostrarי lo fבcil que es.
The only thing you'll come in with hanging from your arm...
Lo תnico que traerבs colgando de tu brazo...
...is a bucket of chicken.
...es una cubeta de pollo.
It was tomato juice.
Era jugo de tomate.
Tomato juice? Man, that's wrong!
Jugo de tomate? ¡Eso estב mal!
- That's wrong. - What's wrong?
- Mal. - Quי estב mal?
I drank the real stuff and he drank tomato juice?
Yo me tomo el de verdad y יl jugo de tomate?
You just got that?
Te acabas de dar cuenta?
Do you know what that stuff did to me?
Sabes el daסo que eso me hizo?
Go to bed, Wayne.
Vete a dormir, Wayne.
- There's some serious repercussions. - Quiet.
- Tuvo repercusiones serias. - Silencio.
Oh, it's on now.
Oh, estב encendido.
Done lit a fuse.
Lista la mecha.
Somebody's gonna get a karate-chop sandwich.
Alguien se comerב un sבndwich picado por un golpe de kבrate.
What are you doing?
Quי haces?
Maybe I'd like to have dinner with my wife.
Quizבs me gustarב cenar con mi esposa.
Let me be real clear with you about something.
Dיjame aclararte algo.
I do not love you.
Yo no te quiero.
Oh, son.
Oh, hijo.
This is when it gets hard.
Aquם es cuando se pone duro.
- Hello, Caleb. - We're done, Dad.
- Hola, Caleb. - Estamos hartos, papב.
I am not gonna keep doing this. I have tried and there's nothing there.
No seguirי con esto. Tratי y no queda nada.
It's not worth it.
No vale la pena.
I understand, son, but you're halfway there...
Te entiendo hijo, pero ya llegaste a la mitad...
...which was the most difficult for us too.
...que fue lo mבs difםcil para nosotros tambiיn.
But at least you had some hope. She has given me nothing.
Pero al menos tenםas esperanzas. Ella no me ha dado nada.
There was a point when we had no hope either.
Hubo un punto en el que no habםa esperanza tampoco.
Our marriage should have ended, Caleb.
Nuestro matrimonio pudo haberse acabado, Caleb.
You can't listen to the way you feel at the moment.
No te dejes llevar por el momento que estבs pasando.
She's seen you trying.
Ella te ha visto intentarlo.
No, she doesn't care, Dad. None of this means anything to her.
No, no le interesa, papב. No significa nada para ella.
Dad, I tried.
Papב, lo intentי.
Caleb, are you off tomorrow?
Estבs libre maסana, Caleb?
Yeah, why?
Sם, por quי?
I'm coming to see you. We can talk then.
Irי a verte maסana. Entonces hablaremos.
Dad, you don't have to do that.
No tienes que hacerlo, papב.
I want to, son. I'd like to come.
Quiero hacerlo, hijo. Quiero ir.
All right.
Estב bien.
Dad, I gotta be honest with you.
Papב, serי honesto contigo.
I feel bad that you drove four hours just to come see me.
Me siento mal de que manejaras cuatro horas solo para verme.
It was good. It gave me time to think and pray.
Fue bueno. Me dio tiempo de pensar y orar.
So, what are you on, Day 20?
En quי dםa estבs, como en el 20?
- Yeah, yeah, something like that. - Yeah.
- Sם, algo asם. - Sם.
I'd say the halfway point was the hardest for us.
Dirםa que la mitad fue lo mבs difםcil para nosotros.
Why?
Por quי?
Well, it's when you determine whether your heart's in it or not.
Porque es cuando te das cuenta de si tu corazףn estב o no.
Makes you check your real motives when things get difficult.
Cuando las cosas se ponen difםciles revisas tus motivos.
Yeah? Did Mom give you a hard time?
Sם? Mamב se puso difםcil?
No. I thought your mother had a pretty good attitude about it.
No. Creo que tu mamב tuvo una actitud muy buena.
Yeah, well, Catherine's not buying any of it.
Sם, bueno, Catherine no cree en nada de esto.
- Why do you think that is? - Because she doesn't love me.
- Por quי crees que es asם? - Porque no me ama.
She doesn't even like me.
Ni siquiera le gusto.
Dad, she's just about ignored everything I've done.
Papב, ha ignorado todo lo que he hecho.
Are you reading everything on each page?
Lees todo lo que estב escrito en cada pבgina?
You mean the Bible verses at the bottom of it?
Los versםculos de la Biblia al final?
No, I'm not, Dad.
No, no los leo, papב.
- I told you, that is not what I need. - And what do you need?
- Te dije que no los necesitaba. - Y quי necesitas?
I need Catherine to wake up to the fact that we are about to get a divorce.
Que Catherine se despierte vea que estamos al borde del divorcio.
And I'm trying to prevent that, but I cannot do it by myself.
Y que yo trato de evitarlo, pero no puedo hacerlo solo.
That may be true, but I think you need more than that.
Puede ser cierto, pero creo que necesitas mבs que eso.
Dad, if you're gonna tell me I need Jesus, please don't.
Papב, si vas a decirme que necesito a Jesתs, no lo hagas.
I don't need a crutch to get through life.
No necesito una muleta para ir por la vida.
Oh, son, Jesus is much more than a crutch.
Oh hijo, Jesתs es mucho mבs que una muleta.
He's become the most significant part of our lives.
Se convertirב en la parte mבs significativa de tu vida.
Dad, why do you keep saying that?
Por quי sigues diciendo eso, papב?
He's the most significant part? How is that?
La parte mבs significativa? Cףmo es eso?
When I realized who I was and who he was...
Cuando me di cuenta de quiיn era yo y quien era יl...
...I realized my need for him.
...descubrם mi necesidad de ֹl.
I needed his forgiveness and salvation.
Necesitaba su perdףn y salvaciףn.
See, I don't understand that.
Mira, no entiendo eso
Why do I need his salvation? What, am I gonna be thrown into hell?
Por quי necesito salvaciףn? Me arrojarבn al infierno?
For what? Because I got divorced?
Por quי? Por divorciarme?
No.
No.
Because you violated his standards.
Porque violaste sus estבndares.
What? Thou shall not kill?
Cuבl? No matarבs?
Dad, I help people. I am a good person.
Papב, yo ayudo a la gente. Soy una buena persona.
According to you.
Segתn tת.
But God doesn't judge by your standards.
Pero Dios no juzga basado en tus estבndares.
- He uses his. - And what are his?
- ֹl usas los suyos. - Y cuבles son?
Well, truth.
Bueno, la verdad.
- Okay. - Love.
- Bien. - El amor.
- I'm honest. - Faithfulness.
- Soy honesto. - La fidelidad.
I care about people. I am those things.
Yo me preocupo por la gente. Soy todo eso.
Sometimes.
A veces.
But have you loved God, the one who gave you life?
Amas a Dios, quien te dio la vida?
His standards are so high, he considers hatred to be murder...
Sus estבndares son tan altos, que considera el odio asesinato...
...and lust to be adultery.
...y la lujuria como adulterio.
Dad, what about all the good I've done?
Y todo el bien que he hecho, papב?
Son, saving someone from a fire does not make you right with God.
Hijo, salvar a alguien en un incendio no te hace mejor para Dios.
You've broken his commandments.
Has violado sus mandamientos.
And one day, you'll answer to him for that.
Y un dםa, tendrבs que responderle por eso.
Caleb...
Caleb...
...if I ask you why you're so frustrated with Catherine...
...Si te preguntara por que estבs tan frustrado con Catherine...
...what would you say?
...Quי me dirםas?
She's stubborn.
Es terca.
She makes everything difficult for me.
Me lo hace todo difםcil.
She's ungrateful.
Es malagradecida.
She's constantly griping about something.
Siempre estב controlando.
Has she thanked you the last 20 days?
Ha agradecido los תltimos 20 dםas?
No.
No.
And you'd think after I washed the car...
Y yo creerםa que despuיs de lavar el auto
...l've changed the oil, do the dishes, clean the house...
...cambiarle el aceite, lavar lo platos, limpiar la casa...
...that she would try to show me a little bit of gratitude.
...podrםa mostrarme un poco de gratitud.
Well, she doesn't.
Pero no lo hace.
In fact, when I come home, she makes me feel like I'm an enemy.
Cuando vuelvo a casa, me hace sentir como un enemigo.
I'm not even welcome in my own home, Dad.
No soy bienvenido en mi propia casa, papב.
That is what really ticks me off.
Eso me molesta mucho.
Dad, for the last three weeks, I have bent over backwards for her.
Papב en las תltimas semanas, me he inclinado ante ella.
I have tried to demonstrate that I still care about this relationship.
He tratado de demostrarle que todavםa me interesa esta relaciףn.
I bought her flowers, which she threw away.
Le comprי unas flores que botף.
I have taken her insults and her sarcasm, but last night was it.
He aguantado sus insultos su sarcasmo, pero anoche se acabף.
I made dinner for her, I did everything I could to demonstrate...
Preparי la cena hice lo que pude para demostrarle...
...that I care about her, to show value for her...
...que la quiero, que la valoro...
...and she spat in my face.
...y ella me escupiף en la cara.
She does not deserve this, Dad. I am not doing it anymore.
Ella no merece esto, papב. No lo harי mבs.
How am I supposed to show love to somebody over and over and over...
Cףmo puedo mostrarle amor a alguien una y otra vez...
...who constantly rejects me?
...que constantemente me rechaza?
That's a good question.
Es una buena pregunta.
Dad, that is not what I'm doing.
Papב, eso no es lo que estoy haciendo.
Isn't it?
No?
No...
No...
Dad, that is not what this is about.
Papב, no se trata de eso.
Son, you just asked me:
Hijo, acabas de preguntarme:
"How can someone show love over and over again...
"Cףmo puedo mostrarle amor a alguien una y otra vez...
...when they're constantly rejected?"
...que constantemente me rechaza?"
Caleb, the answer is:
Caleb, la respuesta es:
You can't love her...
No puedes amarla...
...because you can't give her what you don't have.
...porque no puedes dar lo que no tienes.
I couldn't truly love your mother till I understood what love really was.
No pude amar a tu madre hasta que no entendם que era el amor.
It's not because I get some reward out of it.
No se trata de una recompensa.
I've now made a decision to love your mother...
No tomי la decisiףn de amar a tu madre...
...whether she deserves it or not.
...porque lo mereciera o no.
Son, God loves you even though you don't deserve it.
Hijo, Dios te ama aunque no lo merezcas.
Even though you've rejected him.
Aunque lo rechaces.
Spat in his face.
O le escupas en la cara.
God sent Jesus to die on the cross and take the punishment for your sin...
Dios enviף a Jesתs a morir en la cruz por nuestros pecados...
...because he loves you.
...porque te ama.
The cross was offensive to me until I came to it.
La cruz era ofensiva para mם hasta que fui hacia ella.
But when I did...
Pero cuando lo hice...
...Jesus Christ changed my life.
...Jesucristo cambiף mi vida.
That's when I truly began to love your mom.
Fue cuando comencי a amar a tu madre de verdad.
Son, I can't settle this for you.
Hijo no puedo resolver esto.
This is between you and the Lord.
Es entre tת y el Seסor.
But I love you too much not to tell you the truth.
Pero te amo demasiado como para no decirte la verdad.
Can't you see that you need him?
No ves que lo necesitas?
Can't you see that you need his forgiveness?
No ves que necesitas su perdףn?
Yes.
Sם.
Will you trust him with your life?
Le confiarבs tu vida?
Waffle time.
Hora de waffles.
Hey, man, I'd like to talk to you about something.
Oye, amigo, me gustarםa hablarte de algo.
What's that?
De quי?
- Well... - Hey, captain.
- Bueno... - Hola Capitבn.
I think B shift is trying to pull a joke on us, man.
Creo que el turno B, no estב haciendo una broma.
Salt and pepper shaker won't come apart.
La sal y la pimienta no se separan.
Hey, toss them over here.
Mיzclalas por aquם.
Thanks. Don't forget to mop the kitchen after breakfast.
Gracias, limpiar el piso de la cocina cuando terminemos.
Yes, sir.
Sם, seסor.
You wanna tell me something?
Quieres decirme algo?
It's about your faith.
Sobre la fe.
- My faith? - Yeah.
- Mi fe? - Sם.
What about it?
Quי?
Well, I'm in.
Que me unם.
You're in?
Te uniste?
Yeah, I'm in.
Sם, me unם.
Are you saying that you wanna be in?
Quieres decir que te quieres unir?
- I'm saying I'm in. - You're really in?
- Digo que me unם. - De verdad?
- Really. - You can't be half in and say you're in.
- De verdad. - Crees que te uniste.
- You gotta be all in, brother. - I'm saying I'm all in.
- Tienes que hacerlo todo. - Digo que me unם.
Caleb, I can't believe it, man.
Caleb, no te creo.
- Yeah. - You're my brother.
- Sם. - Eres mi hermano.
- I'm your brother? - Yeah, man.
- Soy tu hermano? - Sם, hombre.
You're my brother from another mother but now we got the same father.
Eres mi hermano de otra madre pero tenemos el mismo padre.
- What? - I'll explain it to you later, man.
- Quי? - Te lo explico luego.
This is awesome.
Esto es increםble.
- Does Catherine know? - No.
- Catherine sabe? - No.
No, I don't think she'd care right now, to tell you the truth.
No creo que le importe.
She hasn't been taking too well to this whole love dare thing.
No se ha tomado muy bien esto del reto del amor.
- But you're not done yet, right? - No, I'm day 21 out of 40.
- Pero no has terminado, no? - No, estoy en el dםa 21 de 40...
But I'll be honest with you. Up to this point...
Pero para se honesto contigo llegado a este punto...
...my heart's not been in it. - That's what matters.
...no lo he hecho de corazףn. - Eso es lo que importa.
A woman can tell when you're just going through the motions.
Una mujer sabe cuando lo estבs haciendo automבticamente.
That's absolutely right.
Eso es cierto.
- Hey, let me ask you a question. - Go ahead.
- Dיjame hacerte una pregunta. - Hazla.
How did you get a good start with Tina?
Cףmo hiciste para tener un buen comienzo con Tina?
Why is it so easy for you?
Por quי es tan fבcil para ustedes?
Oh, it's not always been easy. Marriage takes work, man.
No siempre ha sido fבcil. El matrimonio necesita trabajo.
Tina is an incredible wife.
Tina es una esposa increםble.
But we learned a lot of lessons the hard way.
Pero aprendimos muchas lecciones de la manera mבs difםcil.
At least you haven't had to face divorce.
Al menos no se han enfrentado con un divorcio.
I wish that were true.
Ojalב eso fuera cierto.
What does that mean?
Quי quieres decir?
You and Tina been struggling that much?
Tina y tת han peleado hasta ese punto?
Not me and Tina. But I did with my first wife.
Tina y yo no. Pero sם con mi primera esposa.
What?
Quי?
You were married to someone before Tina?
Te casaste con alguien antes que con Tina?
For one horrible year.
Por un aסo horrible.
I got married for the wrong reasons.
Me casי por las razones equivocadas.
Then I turned around and got a divorce for the wrong reasons.
Y luego me divorciי por las razones equivocadas.
Man, I thought I was just following my heart.
Pensי que estaba haciendo lo que dictaba mi corazףn.
Michael, I've worked with you for five years.
Michael, he trabajado contigo por cinco aסos.
- You've never told me that. - Because I'm not proud of it.
- Nunca me lo contaste. - Porque no me siento orgulloso.
It was before I gave my life to the Lord...
Fue antes de que le entregara mi vida al Seסor...
...and, man, I was just only concerned about my rights and my needs.
...solo me preocupaban mis derechos y mis necesidades.
Man, I ruined her life.
Arruinי su vida.
But when I gave my life to God...
Pero cuando le entreguי mi vida a Dios...
...I tried to find her, but she'd already remarried.
...tratי de encontrarla pero ya se habםa casado con otro.
So believe me when I tell you I got a big scar.
Crיeme cuando te digo que tengo una gran cicatriz.
Man, God made marriage to be for life.
Dios creף el matrimonio para que durara toda la vida.
That's why you gotta keep your vows to Catherine.
Por eso debes mantener tus votos con Catherine.
You gotta beg God to teach you how to be a good husband.
Debes rogarle a Dios que te enseסe como ser un buen esposo.
And don't just follow your heart, man, because your heart can be deceived.
Y no solo seguir a tu corazףn, porque יste puede engaסarse.
But you gotta lead your heart.
Tienes que dirigir a tu corazףn.
It's just been hard for me, you know?
Es que ha sido duro para mם, sabes?
I saw my parents again yesterday...
Vi a mis padres ayer otra vez...
...and, well, Mom's not doing too well.
...y mamב no estב muy bien.
It's amazing how much a stroke can affect somebody's life.
Es increםble lo mucho que un ataque puede afectar una vida.
I just...
Es como...
I feel like she's trapped, you know?
Siento como si ella estuviera atrapada.
And Dad does his best to communicate...
Y papב trata de comunicarse con ella...
...but it's hard for him too.
...pero tambiיn es duro para יl.
Catherine, I'm so sorry.
Catherine, lo siento mucho.
You seem very close to them.
Parece que eres muy cercana con ellos.
I am.
Lo soy.
They had me late in life so it was like growing up with grandparents.
Me tuvieron de viejos, asם que fue como crecer con abuelos.
So they spoiled you.
Te malcriaron.
Hey, now. I think they did a pretty good job.
Oye, creo que hicieron un buen trabajo.
They did. They should be very proud.
Es cierto, deben estar orgullosos.
You know, you're kind of sweet when you wanna be.
Eres como dulce cuando quieres.
Kind of?
"Como"?
With some training, I think you could be a fine gentleman.
Con entrenamiento creo que serםas un caballero.
Well, are you offering lessons?
Estבs ofreciendo lecciones?
So, what does your mom need?
Quי le hace falta a tu mamב?
Well, a better wheelchair and hospital bed...
Una silla de ruedas mejor y una mesa de hospital...
...would be at the top of the list.
...eso serםa lo primero de la lista.
I've been working with RMS Medical Supplies to get them...
He hablado con RMS Suministros Mיdicos para obtenerlas...
...but it's so expensive.
...pero son tan caras.
Well, you can't put a price on helping your mom.
No puedes ponerle precio a la ayuda para tu mamב.
That's right.
Es cierto.
So it's worth the sacrifice.
Vale la pena el sacrificio.
You know, they're lucky to have you for a daughter.
Tienen suerte de que seas su hija.
Don't look at me like that. I'm trying to help.
No me mires asם, trato de ayudar.
Why does it matter what my bed looks like? I sleep in it.
Quי importa como se vea mi cama? Yo soy el que duerme ahם.
What if the chief walks through here? My bed says I take my job seriously.
Y si entra el jefe? Mi cama dice que soy serio en mi trabajo.
Your bed says your mama didn't help you make it up.
La tuya dice que tu mamב no te ayudף a hacerla.
Teaching a rookie how to make his bed?
Le enseסas a un novato a hacer su cama?
Somebody's got to.
Alguien debe hacerlo.
That looks as bad as yours did when I taught you.
Se ve tan mal como cuando yo te enseסי a ti.
Engine 2, Engine 1, Area 1, Battalion 1.
Motor 2, Motor 1, ֱrea 1, Batallףn 1.
Respond to 20911 th Avenue.
Respondan a la avenida 20911 t.
Structure fire, residence. Time out, 15:32.
Incendio en la estructura de un edificio. Tiempo fuera, 15:32.
- Michael, you got that? - Got it.
- Oםste Michael? - Lo oם.
- Wayne, let's roll.
- Wayne, nos vamos - Vamos.
Engine 1 is en route to 20911 th Avenue, structure fire.
Motor 1 en ruta a la avenida 20911 fuego en la estructura.
10-4, Engine 1.
10-4, Motor 1.
Be advised we've received numerous calls regarding this structure fire.
Recuerden que hemos recibido muchas llamadas por el incendio.
That means there's something to this one.
Eso significa que algo pasa.
Make sure you're tightened up.
Fםjate si estבs bien asegurado.
Remember your training. Stay with your partner.
Recuerda el entrenamiento. Quיdate con tu compaסero.
Yes, sir.
Sם, seסor.
Engine 1 is 10-23.
Motor 1 es 10-23.
We have a single-story brick dwelling, 30 percent involved.
Un solo piso, ladrillo, 30 por ciento comprometido.
We'll be using a 1 " and 3-quarter for rescue.
Usaremos una de 69 cm para el rescate.
We'll be 11 th Avenue Command. Engine 2, bring me a line.
Comando de la avenida 11. Motor 2, traiga una lםnea.
Be advised there is a hydrant right next to Engine 1.
Hay un hidrante al lado del Motor 1.
Unit 2's clear. One supply line.
Unidad 2 despejada. Una lםnea de suministro.
Come on, rookie, let's go.
Vamos novato.
You live here? Is everyone out of the house?
Vives aquם? No hay nadie en la casa?
My daughter's in the neighbor's house. This is our home.
Mi hija estב en casa del vecino. Esta es nuestra casa.
- Please, put that fire out. - We will, just stay clear.
- Apaguen el fuego, por favor. - Lo haremos, despejen.
- Please, please. - Oh, no. No.
- Por favor, por favor. - Oh, no. No.
Megan, Megan, where's Lacey?
Megan, Megan, dףnde estב Lacey?
- She went home already. - You mean she's not at your house?
- Se fue a tu casa. - Entonces no estב contigo?
No, I was just talking to her on the phone.
No, acabo de hablar con ella por telיfono.
Lacey!
¡Lacey!
- You can't go in there. - Lacey, no!
- No puedes entrar. - ¡Lacey, no!
- Let me go. Please let me go.
- No puedes entrar... - ¡Suיltame!
My baby!
¡Mi bebי!
- Let's go, let's go. - Come on, guys, let's go.
- Vamos, vamos. - Vamos muchachos.
Lacey!
¡Lacey!
My baby.
Mi bebי.
Come on, guys. Come on, guys.
Vamos muchachos.
Let's go.
Vamos.
- It's done. - Charge.
- Listo. - Carguen.
Lacey!
¡Lacey!
- Get in there, guys, get in there. - Lacey.
- Entren muchachos, entren. - Lacey.
Lacey! Lacey!
¡Lacey! ¡Lacey!
Come on. Over here, man. Over here.
Ven. Por aquם, por aquם.
Back out, back out, back out.
Retrocede, retrocede.
Over here!
¡Aquם!
There's a hydrant over there. Give me one supply line to Engine 1.
Hay un hidrante allם. Lםnea de suministro a Motor 1.
Hey, we got two people inside. We need you.
Hay dos personas adentro. Te necesitamos.
Hey, hurry up with that supply line.
Apresתrense con esa lםnea.
Get back in there, get back in there.
Llיvenla atrבs, llיvenla atrבs.
Breathe. Breathe, Lacey. Breathe for me.
Respira, Lacey. Hazlo por mם.
Captain, you gotta get out of the house. The roof is about to give.
Capitבn, salga de la casa. El techo va a ceder.
Captain, do you read me? You've gotta get out.
Me copia, Capitבn? Tiene que salir.
God, get me out of here. Get us out of here.
Dios, sבcame de aquם. Sבcanos de aquם.
There, there.
Allם, allם.
Get the girl. Get the girl.
Toma a la niסa.
With the x-ray showing that...
Las radiografםas muestran...
...he's left with a partial thickness burn to the arm.
...que tiene una quemadura de grosor parcial en el brazo.
You look terrible.
Te ves terrible.
I feel terrible.
Me siento terrible.
You gonna be okay?
Vas a estar bien?
He sustained some first-degree burns, but he should be fine.
Tiene quemaduras de primer grado, pero estarב bien.
So this is your husband?
Es tu esposo?
- Yes. - You've got a hero on your hands.
- Sם. - Tienes un hיroe contigo.
Sir, I need you to keep this arm elevated for 24 hours...
Seסor necesito que tenga el brazo elevado por 24 horas...
...to help the swelling go down.
...para disminuir la hinchazףn.
Come back in 48 hours to get it checked out again.
Vuelva en 48 horas para revisarlo de nuevo.
- Well, let me get out of your way. - You're not in our way. You can stay.
- Voy a dejar de estorbarles. - No nos estorbas. Quיdate.
No, it's all right. I'll let you do your job.
No, estב bien. Te dejarי hacer tu trabajo.
I'm gonna get you more gauze to take home with you...
Voy a darte mבs gasa para que te lleves...
...and fill that prescription for your pain, okay?
...y toma esta prescripciףn para el dolor, estב bien?
I wouldn't put that ring back on your finger...
Yo no me pondrםa ese anillo...
...until your hand has a chance to heal.
...hasta que tu mano pueda cicatrizar
My hand's gonna have to heal with this ring on my finger.
Mi mano tendrב que sanar con este anillo en el dedo.
Mom, it'll be fine.
Mamב, estarי bien.
It's gonna heal up in a couple of weeks.
Me voy a curar en un par de semanas.
Yes, I got it wrapped up right now. Can I speak with Dad, please?
Sם, lo tengo vendado. Puedo hablar con papב?
Okay, Mom, I got it.
Sם, mamב te entendם.
Now, would you please hand the phone to Dad?
Puedes darle el telיfono a papב?
Thank you.
Gracias.
Dad, would you please ask Mom to cut me some slack?
Podrםas decirle a mamב que me deje tranquilo, papב?
I'm a fireman. I'm gonna be around fires.
Soy bombero. Estoy en incendios.
I know. I know, Dad.
Ya sי, ya sי, papב.
I just don't like getting grilled every time she picks up the phone.
Es que no me gusta que me regaסe cada vez que agarro el telיfono.
Yeah. Today, Day 23.
Sם, hoy dםa 23...
But it was hard this morning.
Pero fue una maסana dura.
Yeah, the newspaper called me twice wanting an interview.
Sם, me llamaron dos veces del periףdico para una entrevista.
Seems I'm a hero with everybody in the world except my wife.
Parece que soy un hיroe para todos menos mi esposa.
No. No, I'm not giving up.
No. No, me rendirי.
Thanks, Dad.
Gracias, papב.
All right, I'll talk to you later.
Bien, hablamos despuיs.
Bye.
Adiףs.
Caleb, what are you doing?
Caleb, quי haces?
Why is this so hard?
Por quי esto es tan difםcil?
Day 23, watch out for parasites.
Dםa 23 cuםdate de los parבsitos.
A parasite is anything that latches onto you or your partner...
Un parבsito es algo que se prende de ti o de tu pareja...
... and sucks the life out of your marriage.
...y succiona la vida de tu matrimonio.
They're usually in the form of addictions like gambling...
Generalmente son adicciones, apuestas...
... drugs or pornography.
...droga o pornografםa.
They promise pleasure, but they grow like a disease...
Prometen placer, pero crecen como una enfermedad...
... and consume more and more of your thoughts, time and money.
...y consumen tu tiempo y tus pensamientos.
They steal away your loyalty and heart from those you love.
Les quitan la lealtad y tu corazףn a los que amas.
Marriages rarely survive if parasites are present.
Los matrimonios raramente sobreviven con parבsitos.
If you love your wife...
Si amas a tu esposa...
... you must destroy any addiction that has your heart.
...destruye cualquier adicciףn que haya en tu corazףn.
If you don't, it will destroy you.
Si no lo haces, te destruirב a ti...
Okay, Lord. No more addictions.
Muy bien, Seסor. No mבs adicciones.
Mr. Rudolph.
Sr. Rudolph.
Caleb.
Caleb.
You doing okay today?
Estב bien?
No, not really.
No mucho.
Irma, I don't want you talking to that guy.
Irma, no quiero que hables con este tipo.
He is weird.
Es raro.
Takes one to know one.
Hace falta uno para conocer al otro.
What?
Quי?
No.
No.
- Good morning. - Hi, Mrs. Evans, how are you?
- Buenos dםas. - Hola, Sra. Evans, cףmo estב?
I'm fine. I hope you are.
Bien, espero que tת tambiיn.
I'm doing pretty good.
Me va bastante bien.
I actually wanted to talk to you about the equipment we've been looking at.
Querםa hablarle del equipo que estבbamos buscando.
I bet your parents are excited. When a patient gets the right wheelchair...
Apuesto a que sus padres estבn entusiasmados, la silla correcta...
...it can make such a difference.
...hace una gran diferencia.
I'm sorry, what?
Disculpe, quי dijo?
The bed and wheelchair we delivered to your parents this morning.
La cama y la silla de ruedas que les entregamos a sus padres.
To my parents?
A mis padres?
Yes, they should have been delivered by now.
Sם, ya deben haberlas recibido.
But I haven't paid for anything yet.
Pero no las he pagado todavםa.
Oh, it's actually already been paid for.
Ya se pagaron.
A gentleman called, said that he wanted to pay...
Un caballero llamף y dijo que יl pagarםa todo...
...for everything that you'd picked out.
...lo que usted escogiף.
Actually, he covered everything plus some accessories.
De hecho cubriף todo, mבs unos accesorios.
He said...
ֹl dijo...
Mrs. Holt?
Sra. Holt?
- Isn't this wonderful? - Oh, she looks amazing.
- No es maravilloso? - Oh, se ve increםble.
Hi, Mom.
Hola, mamב.
Has anyone ever told you that you're wonderful?
Alguien te ha dicho que eres maravilloso?
Maybe, but not today.
Quizבs, pero no esta noche.
Gavin, you didn't have to do that.
Gavin, no tenםas que hacerlo.
- Do what? - Giving money to help my parents.
- Hacer quי? - Pagar para ayudar a mis padres.
That was so thoughtful.
Fue tan considerado.
Thank you.
Gracias.
You're welcome.
De nada.
It was the least I could do.
Era lo menos que podםa hacer.
- Do you have lunch plans? - I do now.
- Tienes planes para almorzar? - Ahora tengo.
"Dear Catherine.
"Querida Catherine.
I can't tell you how much I've enjoyed getting to know you.
No sabes lo mucho que disfruto estar contigo.
I find myself thinking about you often...
Me encuentro pensando en ti a menudo...
...and I look forward to seeing you every day.
...y esperando el momento de verte cada dםa.
Gavin."
Gavin".
Yeah, I need to know if there's a Gavin that works at the hospital.
Sם, necesito saber si en el hospital trabaja un Gavin.
No, I just have a first name.
No, solo sי su primer nombre.
Dr. Keller?
Dr. Keller?
- Yes? - Caleb Holt.
- Sם? - Caleb Holt.
I need a word with you, please.
Necesito hablar con usted.
It's really not a good time. I'm about to make my rounds.
No es un buen momento. Iba a hacer mis rondas.
I think you need to make time.
Creo que deberב hacer tiempo.
This is concerning Catherine, my wife.
Esto es sobre Catherine, mi esposa.
All right, what can I do for you?
Estב bien. Quי puedo hacer por usted?
I know what you're doing.
Sי lo que estב haciendo.
I have no intention of stepping aside as you try to steal my wife's heart.
No tengo intenciones de apartarme mientras conquista a mi esposa.
I've made some mistakes, but I still love her.
He cometido errores, pero todavםa la amo.
So just know I am going after her too.
Asם que sepa que lucharי por ella tambiיn.
And since I'm married to her, I'd say I've got a head start.
Y como estamos casados, yo dirםa que tenemos un comienzo.
By the way, thanks for helping me with my hand.
Por cierto, gracias por ayudarme con mi mano.
My ring finger's feeling a whole lot better.
El dedo del anillo estב mucho mejor.
Y'all, I just saw Caleb and Dr. Keller going at each other.
Oigan acabo de ver a Caleb y al Dr. Keller peleando.
He had his fist all knuckled in his face.
Le dio con el puסo en la cara.
Are you serious?
Es en serio?
What are you all talking about?
De quי estבs hablando?
Hey, Cat, how you doing, girl?
Hola, Cat, cףmo te va?
I'm fine. You sure got quiet really fast.
Estoy bien. Estבs muy callada.
Well, that's because we decided to stop talking.
Eso es porque decidimos no hablar mבs.
What's up?
En quי andas?
I'm setting up an interview in about 10 minutes...
Organizando una entrevista en diez minutos...
...but I was wondering if you guys have seen Dr. Keller this morning.
...pero me preguntaba si habםan visto al Dr. Keller.
I think he was doing rounds, maybe on the 8th Floor.
Creo que estב en sus rondas, tal vez en el piso 8.
Okay, well, I'll see y'all later.
Te verי luego.
See you.
Nos vemos.
Why didn't you tell her?
Por quי no le contaste?
- Because it ain't our business. - But you told all of us.
- Porque no es asunto nuestro. - Pero nos contaste a nosotros.
I don't want her to know her business is our business if it ain't our business.
No quiero que sepa que sus asuntos son nuestros cuando no lo son.
Hi.
Hola.
Hey, how are you?
Hola, cףmo estבs?
- Hey, Catherine. - How's the good doctor today?
- Hola, Catherine. - Cףmo estב el buen doctor?
- Pretty busy, actually. - Are we still on for lunch?
- Muy ocupado. - Confirmados para el almuerzo?
You know, there's a few things I need to catch up on.
Tengo un par de cosas que adelantar.
- I've gotten a little behind lately. - Okay.
- Voy retrasado. - Estב bien.
- Well, maybe we could talk later. - That'd be good.
- Podrםamos hablar despuיs. - Serםa bueno.
- All right, see you around. - See you.
- Muy bien, nos vemos. - Nos vemos.
- Hello, Catherine. - Oh, hi, Anna. How are you?
- Hola, Catherine. - Oh, hola, Anna. Cףmo estבs?
I'm doing well. And you?
Bien, y tת?
I'm okay, I guess. Do you wanna sit down?
Bien, creo. Quieres sentarte?
I'd love to if I'm not disturbing you.
Me encantarםa si no te molesto.
Not at all.
Para nada.
So, what's been going on in your life these days?
Cףmo ha estado tu vida estos dםas?
We haven't talked in a while.
No hemos hablado hace un tiempo.
Well, it's been one of those years.
Ha sido uno de esos aסos.
Good or bad?
Bueno o malo?
You know, I hate to say it, but mostly bad.
Odio decirlo, pero malo mayormente.
You know when you get to a fork in the road...
Como cuando llegas a una encrucijada y sabes...
...and you know that either way you go is gonna change your life?
...que cualquier camino cambiarב tu vida?
Life does give you some of those. Excuse me just a minute.
La vida te da eso. Discתlpame un momento.
So have you decided which path to take?
Ya decidiste quי camino tomar?
I think so.
Eso creo.
It's just hard not to second-guess yourself.
Es difםcil no saber elegir.
Pardon me, I don't mean to pry, but does this concern relationships?
No quiero indagar, pero tiene que ver con relaciones?
It does.
Sם.
Catherine, you're so young.
Catherine, eres tan joven.
I would encourage you to make your choices carefully.
Te dirםa que escogieras cuidadosamente.
I'm trying to.
Trato.
But I'm also tired of feeling empty.
Pero estoy harta de sentirme vacםa.
Anna, it's so nice to have someone treat you...
Anna, es tan agradable que alguien te trate...
...like they really care about you.
...como si le importaras.
Forgive me, but you're talking about a certain young doctor, aren't you?
Estבs hablando de cierto doctor?
I suppose it's no secret as much as he and I talk.
Supongo que no es un secreto lo mucho que hablamos.
I couldn't help but notice how you act around each other.
No pude evitar notar que estבn mucho juntos.
But I also wonder how your husband would feel.
Me pregunto como se siente tu esposo.
My husband has had his chance.
Mi esposo tuvo su oportunidad.
And Dr. Keller is a good man.
Y el Dr. Keller es un buen hombre.
He treats me better than my husband has treated me in years.
Me trata mejor de lo que me ha tratado mi esposo en aסos.
He listens to me and makes me feel important.
Me escucha y me hace sentir importante.
I haven't felt that way in a very long time.
No me he sentido asם en mucho tiempo.
It's always good to have that, but...
Es bueno sentir eso...
But, sweetheart, if this doctor is trying to woo you while you're still married...
Pero querida el doctor trata de conquistarte aתn estando casada...
...what makes you think he won't do that with someone else?
...quי te hace pensar que no lo hace con otras?
I don't wanna talk about this, Anna. We're getting personal.
No quiero hablar de esto Anna. Se estב poniendo muy personal
Oh, Catherine, I'm sorry.
Oh, Catherine, disculpa.
I didn't mean to overstep my bounds.
No quise entrometerme.
I need to go. It's good to see you, Anna.
Debo irme, fue bueno verte, Anna.
Catherine, are you okay?
Catherine, estבs bien?
I'm fine.
Estoy bien.
- Aren't you going to work? - No.
- No irבs a trabajar? - No.
- Are you sick? - I'll be fine.
- Estבs enferma? - Estarי bien.
Is it your allergies?
Son tus alergias?
I said I'll be fine. Don't worry about me.
Te dije que estarי bien. No te preocupes por mם.
Because if you need something, I can go to the store.
Si necesitas algo puedo comprבrtelo.
No, I'm okay. You can go.
No, estoy bien. Puedes irte.
Okay.
Estב bien.
Can you sit up for me?
Te puedes sentar?
You got a fever.
Tienes fiebre.
Here.
Toma.
You think you can take this?
Crees que puedes tomar esto?
Why are you doing this?
Por quי haces esto?
I have learned you never leave your partner.
He aprendido que no se deja atrבs a tu compaסero.
Especially in a fire.
Especialmente en incendios.
Caleb, what's happened to you?
Caleb, quי te pasף?
Dad asked me if there was anything in me...
Papב me preguntף si alguna parte de mם...
...that wanted to save our marriage.
...querםa salvar nuestro matrimonio.
And then he gave me something.
Y luego me dio algo.
I could let you read it.
Puedes leerlo.
Was it this?
Es esto?
How long have you known?
Hace cuבnto lo sabes?
I found it yesterday.
Lo encontrי ayer.
So, what day are you on?
En quי dםa estבs?
Forty-three.
Cuarenta y tres.
There's only 40.
Solo son 40.
Who says I have to stop?
Quiיn dijo que habםa que detenerse?
Caleb...
Caleb...
...I don't know how to process this.
...No sי quי pensar de esto.
This is not normal for you.
No es normal en ti.
Welcome to the new normal.
Bienvenida a la nueva normalidad.
You didn't wanna do this at first, did you?
Al principio no querםas hacerlo, no?
No.
No.
But halfway through, I realized...
Pero a la mitad me di cuenta...
...that I did not understand what love was.
...de que no sabםa lo que era el amor.
And once I understood that, I wanted to do it.
Y cuando lo entendם, quise hacerlo.
Caleb, I want to believe that this is real.
Caleb, quiero creer que esto es real.
But I am not ready to say that I trust you again.
Pero aתn no estoy lista para decir que confםo en ti.
I understand that.
Entiendo.
But whether you ever reach that point or not...
Pero si llegaras o no a ese punto.
...I need you to understand something.
...necesito que entiendas algo.
I am sorry.
Lo siento.
I have been so selfish.
Haber sido tan egoםsta.
For the past seven years, I have trampled on you...
Por siete aסos te he pisoteado...
...with my words and with my actions.
...con mis palabras y mis actos.
I have loved other things when I should have loved you.
He amado otras cosas cuando debםa amarte a ti.
In the last few weeks...
En las תltimas semanas...
...God has given me a love for you that I had never had before.
...Dios me ha dado mבs amor por ti del que nunca sentם.
And I have asked him to forgive me.
Y le he pedido que me perdone.
And I am hoping, I am praying...
Y espero y oro para que...
...that somehow you would be able to forgive me too.
...de alguna forma puedas perdonarme tambiיn.
Catherine, I do not want to live the rest of my life without you.
Catherine, no quiero vivir el resto de mi vida sin ti.
I'm supposed to give those divorce papers...
Debםa darle los papeles del divorcio a mi abogado...
...to my lawyer next week.
...la semana entrante.
I just...
Pero...
I need some time...
...necesito tiempo...
...to think.
...para pensar.
You can have all the time you need.
Tienes todo el tiempo que necesites.
- Hello, Mrs. Holt, how are you today? - Fine, thanks.
- Hola Sra. Holt, Cףmo estב? - Bien, gracias.
I hope your parents are doing well.
Espero que a sus padres les vaya bien.
That new bed and wheelchair are certainly helping.
La nueva cama y la silla estבn ayudando.
I'm so glad. Well, what can I do for you today?
Me alegra. Quי puedo hacer por usted?
I just need to pick up a few linens for the hospital bed for my mom.
Necesito unas sבbanas del hospital para mamב.
Sure, we have some in stock.
Claro tenemos varias.
Great, that's the only thing that wasn't covered by the doctor...
Fue lo תnico que no comprף el doctor...
...when he purchased that bed and wheelchair.
...cuando pago la silla y la cama.
The doctor?
El doctor?
Yes, Dr. Keller, our secret philanthropist.
Sם, Dr. Keller, nuestro filבntropo secreto.
I don't think Dr. Keller covered those things.
No creo que fuera el Dr. Keller quien cubriף con eso.
No, I'm sure he did. I spoke with him about it.
No, estoy segura. Le hablי de eso.
Mrs. Holt, if I remember correctly, $24,300 was given...
Mrs. Holt, si mal no recuerdo, 24.300 dףlares se dieron...
...for the bed and wheelchair, but Dr. Keller was not the main giver.
...por la cama y la silla, pero Dr. Keller no fue quien mבs donף.
What?
Quי?
Of the amount given, Dr. Keller gave $300.
Del total el dio 300 dףlares.
Then who gave the other?
Quiיn dio lo demבs?
Your husband, Caleb.
Tu esposo, Caleb.
He came in about two weeks ago and paid for everything.
Vino hace dos semanas y pagף todo.
I assumed you knew.
Pensי que lo sabםas.
Two weeks ago?
Hace dos semanas?
Yes, he told me not to tell anyone, but I didn't think that included you.
Sם, me dijo que no le dijera a nadie, no pensי que te incluםa.
It was the Tuesday before last.
Fue el martes anterior.
He called and asked what the price...
Llamף y preguntף cual era el precio...
...of a particular bed and wheelchair were.
...de una cama y una silla de ruedas particulares.
And I looked it up and...
Lo busquי y...
Oh, where is it?
Dףnde estב?
Oh, stop crying.
Oh, deja de llorar.
Okay, explain RECEO.
Bien, explica RECEO.
He ain't gonna get it.
No lo tendrב.
Rescue, exposure, containment, extinguish...
Rescate, exposiciףn, contener, extinguir...
Captain, can I see you for a minute?
Capitבn, puedo verlo un minuto?
- Right now? - Yes, sir.
- Ahora? - Sם, seסor.
Something wrong?
Pasa algo malo?
Catherine is in the bay.
Catherine estב en la bahםa.
- My Catherine? - Yes, sir.
- Mi Catherine? - Sם, seסor.
Catherine?
Catherine?
If I haven't told you...
Si no te he dicho que eres...
...that you are a good man...
...un buen nombre...
...you are.
...pues lo eres.
And if I haven't told you...
Y si no te he dicho...
...that I've forgiven you...
...que te perdono...
...I have.
...Ya lo hice. Y si no te he dicho...
...that I love you...
...que te amo...
...I do.
...Te amo.
Something has changed in you, Caleb.
Algo cambiף en ti, Caleb.
And I want what happened to you to happen to me.
Y quiero que me pase lo que te pasף a ti.
It can.
Puede pasarte.
Is it too late to ask you to grow old with me?
Es muy tarde para pedirte que envejezcamos juntos?
- Yes. - Hey, what are you looking at?
- Sם. - Quי estבn mirando?
Back up. There ain't nothing to see here.
Atrבs. No hay nada que ver.
Why? What's going on?
Por quי? Quי pasa?
Go back to your business. Caleb's starting a fire.
De vuelta al trabajo, Caleb estב encendiendo un fuego.
- Why's he starting a...? - Ain't that kind of fire.
- Por quי estב...? - No es esa clase de fuego.
Go back to your business. Go... Hey.
Vuelvan al trabajo.
Put you on cleanup duty.
O los pondrי a limpiar.
Good morning, Mr. and Mrs. Rudolph.
Buenos dםas, Sr. And Sra. Rudolph.
Caleb.
Caleb.
I don't understand that boy.
No entiendo a ese muchacho.
- How are you? - Hi, son.
- Cףmo estבs? - Hola, hijo.
I'm getting to where I know this trail pretty well.
Vuelvo a donde conozco bien la senda.
- You're welcome to walk it anytime. - I just might.
- Bienvenido. - Pero podrםas.
I wanna thank you, Dad.
Quiero agradecerte, papב.
The love darRepoe changed my life.
El reto del amor cambiף mi vida.
God changed your life.
Dios cambiף tu vida.
The love dare was just a tool he used.
El reto del amor fue la herramienta que usף.
I've already given it to one of my firemen.
Ya se lo pasי a uno de mis compaסeros.
Good. It's meant to be passed on.
Bien, estב hecho para pasarlo.
I just can't tell you how grateful I am that you didn't give up on me, Dad.
No sabes cuanto te agradezco que no te rindieras conmigo, papב.
Or on Mom, for that matter.
Lo mismo mamב.
Caleb, I wanna be a godly man.
Caleb, quiero ser un hombre de Dios.
And I'm learning so much.
Y estoy aprendiendo tanto.
But there's something I haven't told you.
Pero hay algo que no te he dicho.
I wrote that notebook in my own handwriting...
Escribם ese cuaderno con mi letra...
...because I knew you would accept it from me.
...porque sabםa que lo aceptarםas de mם...
But I didn't do the love dare on your mom.
Pero yo no hice el reto del amor con tu mamב.
She did it to me.
Ella lo hizo conmigo.
What?
Quי?
Son...
Hijo...
...I was the one that wanted to leave.
...yo era el que querםa marcharme.
But God got ahold of your mother...
Pero Dios tomo a tu madre...
...and she prayed and loved me unconditionally.
...y ella orף y me amף incondicionalmente.
It was through her example that I came to Christ.
Fue con su ejemplo que lleguי a Cristo.
Mom did this?
Mamב hizo esto?
She's such a blessing to me.
Ella es mi bendiciףn.
And she's grown so much.
Y ha crecido tanto.
I love her with all my heart.
La amo con toda mi alma.
Dad, I...
Papב, yo...
I have treated her so wrong.
La he tratado tan mal.
Caleb, she deserves your respect.
Caleb, ella merece tu respeto.
Mom. Mom, I'm so sorry.
Mamב, lo siento tanto.
Mom, I didn't know. I didn't know.
No lo sabםa, mamב.
It's all right, son. It's okay. It's all right.
Estב bien, hijo. Estב bien.
Mom, please forgive me.
Por favor perdףname, mamב.
I do, Caleb. You're forgiven.
Estבs perdonado, Caleb.
I love you.
Te quiero.
I love you too, Mom.
Yo tambiיn te quiero mamב.
I love you so much.
Te quiero tanto.
I love you, Caleb.
Te quiero, Caleb.
We've gathered here today to celebrate the reaffirmation of vows...
Nos hemos reunido aquם para la renovaciףn de los votos...
...with Caleb and Catherine.
...de Caleb y Catherine.
This may be the second time they've made a commitment to this marriage...
Esta puede ser la segunda vez que se comprometen con su matrimonio...
...it is the first time they've done so on a foundation of faith in Jesus Christ.
...pero es la primera vez que lo hacen basados en Jesucristo.
"It is the desire of Caleb and Catherine...
"Es el deseo de Caleb y Catherine...
...to establish their vows from this point on...
...establecer sus votos de aquם en adelante...
...as a covenant and not a contract.
...como un pacto y no como un contrato.
For marriage is a sacred institution established by God...
Porque el matrimonio es una instituciףn sagrada de Dios...
...and one that is meant to last for life."
...hecha para durar toda la vida".
"Caleb, in the presence of God and these witnesses...
"Caleb, en presencia de Dios y estos testigos...
...do you come today to freely and unconditionally commit...
...vienes hoy, libre e incondicionalmente comprometido...
...to this covenant marriage to Catherine?"
...a este pacto matrimonial con Catherine?"
I do.
Sם.
"And, Catherine, do you come today to freely and unconditionally commit...
...vienes hoy, libre e incondicionalmente comprometida...
...to this covenant marriage to Caleb?"
...a este pacto matrimonial con Caleb?"
I do.
Sם.
With all my heart.
Con todo mi corazףn.
Genesis 2:24 says:
Gיnesis 2:24 dice:
For this reason, a man shall leave his father and mother...
Por esta razףn, el hombre dejarב a su padre y a su madre...
...and shall be joined to his wife, and the two shall become one flesh.
...y se unirב a su esposa para ser una sola carne.